<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Useful instructions for a professing people in times of great security and degeneracy delivered in several sermons on solemnm occasions / by Mr. Samuel Willard ...</title>
            <author>Willard, Samuel, 1640-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 207 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66112</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2299</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38936</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18196698</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18196698</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107003</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66112)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107003)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1137:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Useful instructions for a professing people in times of great security and degeneracy delivered in several sermons on solemnm occasions / by Mr. Samuel Willard ...</title>
                  <author>Willard, Samuel, 1640-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Samuel Green,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge (Mass.) :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, with print show-through; torn with loss of print; best copy available for photographing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Congregationalism --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107003:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SEF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L INSTR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CTIONS for a profeſſing People in Times of great</hi> SECURITY AND DEGENERACY: Delivered in ſeveral SERMONS on Solemn Occaſions:</p>
            <p>By Mr. <hi>Samuel Willard</hi> Paſtor of the Church of Chriſt at <hi>Groton.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>Ezek. 3. 17.</bibl>
            <q>Son of Man, I have made thee a Watchman to the Houſe of Iſrael: therefore hear the Word at my mouth, and give them warning from me.</q>
            <bibl>Amos 3. 8.</bibl>
            <q>The Lord God hath ſpoken, who can but Propheſy?</q>
            <bibl>Jer. 2. 31.</bibl>
            <q>O Generation, See ye the Word of the Lord: have I been a wilderneſs unto Iſrael? a Land of darkeneſs? wherefore ſay my People, we are Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, we will come no more unto thee.</q>
            <bibl>Haggai. 1. 5, 7.</bibl>
            <q>Thus ſaith the Lord, Conſider your wayes.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>CAMBRIDGE: Printed by Samuel Green.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1673</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:107003:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107003:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To his Beloved Friends the Inhabitants of GROTON.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat it was not a deſire to appear in publick, but to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer your requeſts, gave light to the enſuing Sermons, ye are my witneſſes, and that in the publiſhing of them, I have no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> endeavoured to va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>niſh and paint them over with flouriſhes of men pleaſing words; the thing it ſelf may ſpeak: in the reading you ſhall finde nothing but what was delivered in Preaching. Touching the occaſion of them I need not advertiſe you, you may well enough call to minde, the loud voice of ſpeaking pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>idences, which for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad me in ſuch a day to be ſilent: The ſad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>andof God whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was upon the poor poſſeſſed Creature, which produced that on <hi>Iſai. 26. 9.</hi> hath ſounded through this Wilderneſs, but you were eye witneſſes of it; the Lord affect your hearts, and give you to learn righteouſneſs. The other two were alſo upon ſolemn Occaſions, the hand of God upon this Land, and us in particular, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ids Miniſters to cry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud; the Lord God hath ſpoken, who can but Propheſie? I know mans corruption is not willing to becloſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly dealt withal, but I hope many of you have not ſo learned Chriſt. My hearts deſire and prayer for you is, <hi>that you may be prepared for ſhaking times, and the nearer they approach the more need have we to be haſtened and rouſed from our loytering.</hi> If theſe poor labours of mine, may help in that great buſineſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>have my ends fully anſwered; and my deſire for you is, <hi>that thoſe affections may be blown up again in the reading which were kindled in the preaching;</hi> I know I have but a while to be among you, if God pleaſe to mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> me by theſe, or any other weak endeavours, to be under him inſtrumental of your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> good, I ſhall dye with joy; <hi>and ſo meet you all at the right hand of our Judge in that great day, is the higheſt ambition of</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your unworthy Miniſter. S. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107003:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Jer. 7. 12.</bibl>
               <q>But go ye now unto my Place which is in Shiloh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the beginning of this Chapter, the Lord ſends by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, to call Judah and Jeruſalem to <hi>true Repentance;</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courageing them to it by a <hi>promiſe of eſtabliſhment</hi> of their peace and mercies, in caſe they would ſo do. <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. 1, 2, 3, &amp;</hi> 5 6, 7. &amp;c. That this counſell of his may take effect upon them, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to reclaim them from their vain confidence in their <hi>external worſhip,</hi> and enjoyment of the Temple and Ordinances, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. After which he enlargeth himſelfe by a Declaration, of their hypoc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> dealings, and falſe truſt in the Temple, as if it were a ſure ſafe g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rd t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them from puniſhment, notwithſtanding all their wicked abom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons, <hi>ver.</hi> 8, 9, 10. which vanity, he declares to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a changing of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>holy worſhip,</hi> into a <hi>den of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>obhers, ver.</hi> 11. and then gives them to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that he takes notice of it: And in the Text further <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> off from their vain confidence by ſending them to <hi>Shiloh,</hi> to take notice of his dealing with them for thir ſins.</p>
            <p>From the context, diverſe Truths are Obſervable.</p>
            <p>Doct. 1. <hi>When God is never ſo much provoked with a people, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> yet tenders them termes of peace, before he cutts them off.</hi> In the th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> laſt verſes of the former Chapter, he ſhews what they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious and counſelleſs people, on whom he had laid out much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> whom he had ſent many meſſengers, who had ſpent their breath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> lives to no purpoſe, and yet here again he ſends an invitation to re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tance, with a conditional promiſe of good; before he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> laſt ſentence againſt them. The like we ſhall find. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 3. 1. and 18. 11. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reaſon 1. <hi>From the great deſire which God hath that ſinners ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e:</hi> that he may verifie that truth. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>8 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. That ſinners<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> know where the true and proper cauſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their deſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ction <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is in <hi>themſelves,</hi> and not in him; they ſhall not have the blame to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon God in the leaſt, and therefore he pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ers <hi>pardon</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> holds out the <hi>flag of peace</hi> before them, that if in the time of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> will come in, they may, and welcome.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:107003:4"/>
            <p>Reaſ. 2. <hi>From the Attributes of mercy and long-ſuffering,</hi> which diſcover themſelves in withholding the ſtroak of vengeance, and hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his hand back. <hi>Ier. 3. 12. 2 Pet.</hi> 3. 9. God will have a time for all his Attributes to appear, now is the day of <hi>mercy,</hi> and now God will let ſinners have large truſts of it, he <hi>warns,</hi> yea, follows on to <hi>warne</hi> and perſwade with a people; that if it be poſſible they may eſcape</p>
            <p>Reaſ. 3. <hi>For the advancement of his glory by his patience,</hi> God a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at himſelf, his own glory in all his doings: now by this Clemency of his he will gaine honour, either to his <hi>mercy</hi> in their <hi>welfare,</hi> or his <hi>juſtice</hi> in their <hi>ruine;</hi> which every way God will be a gainer hereby: if they <hi>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pent,</hi> how will they magnifie his <hi>patience and ſo bearance:</hi> if they be <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bſtinate and periſh,</hi> how eminently will he clear his <hi>juſtice</hi> in their <hi>ruine?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Uſe 1. <hi>This may convince us how unreaſonable a thing it is to ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God:</hi> is God ſo unwilling to puniſh, ſo deſirous to do us good, ſo ready to pardon us, who would ſin againſt, and provoke ſuch a God? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>old, preſumptuous, and horrible is that ſpirit of iniquity, that makes Gods patience and mercy his encouragement to ſin; would we deal ſo by man, who would take encoucagement? to vex and anger one that is good and patient to us: that is the aggravation of their ſin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6. 43. their deliverances were the occaſion of their preſumption to ſin.</p>
            <p>Uſe 2. What encouragement is there here to us after all our <hi>grievous ſins?</hi> to return to the Lord by Repentance, God is yet ready to receive us, and r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtore his mercies unto us, and therefore let us be quickned up by this conſideration. motive.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Conſider the wonderful ſelf denyal that there is in God,</hi> he needs us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot, but could do well enough without us, being ſelf-ſufficient in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, yea, hath Angels which attend upon him, and that he ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ept of duſt and aſhes, much more unprofitable ſinful creatures, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ceive them into mercy; oh what a condeſcendency is this!</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Conſider, the wrong we do him will fall upon our ſelves in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> may fight againſt him, but they are arrows ſhot up againſt heaven, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ich will fall down upon our own heads. <hi>Ier.</hi> 7. 19. we may think <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat we will, but the iſſue of ſuch provocations, will be the imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t ſinners confuſion; <hi>briers and thorns</hi> muſt not think to thrive againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>devouring fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Conſider, <hi>The benefits of Repentance will redound to our own good.</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:107003:4"/> Jer. 7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5, 6, 7. we ſhall taſt the ſweet of it; to eſcape from miſery, to enjoy the benediction of God, and ſweet fruits of peace, will be our advantage: let it then break our hearts to conſider, that after all our ſins, God hath yet wid'ned arms to receive us into: <hi>if a man find his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, would he not deſtroy them.</hi> 1. Sam. 24. 19. yet hath God had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold opportunities and ſufficient provocations, and hath not made uſe of them.</p>
            <p>Doct. 2. <hi>True Repentance is the beſt and only way for the ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of true peace:</hi> this the Lord propounds to them as the way and means to ſettlement, that they may dwell in that place for ever: and to that end he calls them up, not to a feigned, but a true repentance; if they had a deſire to proſper. <hi>Ier. 4. 1. if you will return, return to me.</hi> i. e. be ſure to repe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t aright, do not turn from one ſin to another, do not wander from that <hi>mountain</hi> to this <hi>hill,</hi> change one Idol for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but go <hi>back again to your God:</hi> hence the Lord ſhews that to be the reaſon of the continuance of their ſorrows. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 2, 3, 4. and <hi>Zech.</hi> 7. 5, 6. they had pretended ſervices, faſtings, <hi>&amp;c. but they did i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not to God,</hi> it was not in a right manner.</p>
            <p>Reaſ. 1. <hi>From the difference between true and feigned repentance,</hi> in the one there is a free and hearty renouncing of all ſin: a ſight of it, a ſorrow for it, and a forſaking it; this the Lord himſelf hath conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as the way to enjoy mercy. <hi>Prov.</hi> 28. 13. this hath a firme promiſe made to it. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 19, 20. when as feigned repentance is a mocking of God, as the Lord declares, and therefore denounceth that threatning againſt it <hi>Iſa. 29. 13, 14. God will not be mocked</hi> by ſinners; that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance which God will only own and acknowledge, comes from a deep touch and ſence of the bitterneſs of ſin. <hi>Ier.</hi> 2. 19.</p>
            <p>Reaſ. 2. <hi>Becauſe it is only true Repentance which ſets us in the way of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> true peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. God only is the Author of true peace. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57. 17. if ever the creature be truly enſtated in peace, God muſt ſpeake it to the ſoule, though all the world ſhould declare amity with the creature, yet if God do not ſet his ſeal to it, it is but a blank, and ſignifies nothing</p>
            <p n="2">2. Sin hath cut the creature off from the <hi>right and true foundation of peace, what peace,</hi> &amp;c. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 9. 22. God will not, cannot, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce bleſſings and peace to impenitent and hypocritical ſinners; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> would wound the great <hi>Attribute</hi> of his holineſs, if he ſhould ſo d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. It is only by true Repentance that we <hi>heartily renounce</hi> ſin, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:107003:5"/> under the condition of peace. <hi>Ier.</hi> 3. 12, 13. God ſets forth tenders of peace before vile ſinners, but there are Articles of <hi>compoſition,</hi> terms of <hi>agreement,</hi> which the Creature muſt needs conſent to, if he deſire good, or otherwiſe the treaty muſt break off, and be put to an end.</p>
            <p>Uſe 1. Here <hi>ſee the dangerous eſtate of an obſtinate people,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to hearken to the counſels of God; if once iniquity increaſe to obſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>acy, and renounce repentance the only way of pacification, the condition of ſuch a people is become deſperate, <hi>Ezek</hi> 14 13 as long as there remains any remorſe upon the conſciences of a people there may be ſome hope of them, becauſe they are not without capacity of attending the way of peace, but if conſcience be ſtupified, and the ſenſe of ſin obliterated, what hope can there be; and therefore as we would avoid utter ruine, have a care of adding obſtinacy to all other ſins, if we will yet repent there is hope, but if we are reſolute our caſe is paſt hope.</p>
            <p>Uſe 2 To direct us to a <hi>right way of ſettling our ſelves in ſuch a firm way of peace as ſhall ſtand;</hi> let us forſake our ſins and return unto God from whom we have turned away; though we have departed away from God into ſin, yet let us not ſtand it out againſt him: <hi>Moti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Conſider, <hi>Our league with Hell and Death will not do, Iſai.</hi> 28. 18 we may go down to <hi>Egypt</hi> and ride upon Horſes, but theſe ſhall not ſave us, <hi>Iſa. 31 beginning,</hi> though we ſhould adde to own the ſtrength of all the Creation, and engage the whole world in our quarrel, yet we muſt not think to be too hard for the Almighty, none ever tryed a fall with him but they were thrown.</p>
            <p n="2">2 So long as we perſiſt in a way of ſin <hi>God hath a quarrel againſt us, Iſai: 57: ult:</hi> wherever God finds wickedneſs there he ſtands off from the ſinner; we may make flouriſhes of great matters in forms of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, &amp;c: but if ſin be ſtill covenanted with, and we maintain our rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, the return will be, <hi>who required theſe things at your hands?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 No peace like that whoſe <hi>foundation is laid in true repentance,</hi> for its a peace whoſe <hi>Baſis</hi> is peace with God, and that gives peace with all things, <hi>Job</hi> 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 19: and its an inviolable peace, a league which can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be broken: Oh! labour we then after this peace, if we clap up a peace and God be not in it, be will diſanul all that is done, but enter a covenant with him and the world ſhall never be able to overthrow it, Earth and Hell ſhall not prevail againſt it; let us then confeſs our ſins to him, and caſt our ſelves before him, and go with them, <hi>Hoſ:</hi> 14: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>:</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:107003:5"/>
            <p>Doct: 3 <hi>True repentance is alwayes attended with a through refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation:</hi> If ye throughly amend your wayes, &amp;c <hi>ver:</hi> 5. the Lord there declares what a manner of repentance it is that he looks for; not a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal, in a few empty Confeſſions, nor a formal, in a few dejected and caſt down looks: like theirs in <hi>Iſai: 58: beginning</hi> but here, and in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel he declares if they will have peace what it is he expects; the ſum of which is, let all which hath been amiſs be mended, turn over a new leaf, reform your hearts and wayes, your ſouls and lives, and that I will accept of.</p>
            <p>Reaſ. 1 <hi>Becauſe ſuch is the vile and loathſome nature of ſin, that can't be indeed ſeen in its own colours, but it muſt needs be odious and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable in our eyes:</hi> It hath ſo much of contrariety in it, to the holineſs of God, and ſo much vileneſs, and filth, and abomination that none can ſee it but muſt needs hate it; when ſin i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> truly ſeen, it then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to be ſinful, <hi>Rom:</hi> 7: 14: that is the very worſt name that can be put upon it, <hi>viz:</hi> its own: men ſee ſin many times in its effects, and that frights them, but it cannot make them hate their ſin, but they think it good enough if it had not ſuch conſequences, but when the face of it is uncovered and the ſouls eyes opened, now he ſtands off, his affections are ſlain.</p>
            <p>Reaſ. 2 <hi>From the Inconſiſtency of hating ſin in the heart, and cloſing with it in the life and practice:</hi> will we alwayes keep company, and hold intimate fellowſhip, and drive a conſtant trade and commerce with one, the ſight of whom we loath; an unreformed life is a plain denial, and contradicting of all our verbal and profeſſed repentance, <hi>Tit:</hi> 1: 16: if we live in ſin it makes nothing to the credit of the world, much leſs to the allſeeing eye of God to ſpeak and profeſs againſt it.</p>
            <p>Reaſ: 3 <hi>From the nature of true repentance, which is a change from what we were to ſome other thing;</hi> a change of affections, a change of profeſſion, and not only ſo, but alſo a change of objects, a turning from the creature to God, <hi>Jer:</hi> 4: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: now this implies a through reformation when the creature caſts off all other things which it hath purſued, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſeek to God alone.</p>
            <p>Uſe 1 This may call us to the Examination, <hi>Whether ever we truly repented or no of thoſe ſins which we have ſo often confeſſed to God,</hi> viz: <hi>where is our reformation?</hi> Search throughly one and another of us, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what we have confeſſed, and with what ſhews of ſenſe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, as if thoſe ſins had indeed been a burthen to us, and we deſire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:107003:6"/> be rid of them, but have they been amended, have we truly relinquiſht them? if not, aſſure we our ſelves God looks at himſelf as mocked at all this while, and therefore if we be defective in this eſſential and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial part of our repentance, never enquire or ask of God where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his hand is ſtretched out ſtill againſt us, after ſo many Prayers and ſupplications have been poured out before him on ſolemn dayes:</p>
            <p>The Reaſon is obvious and plain, and he that runs may read it:</p>
            <p>Uſe 2 Hence therefore let this truth move upon us, <hi>to perſwade us, and to reclaim us from words to works; from profeſſion to practiſe, from confeſſion to amendment:</hi> we have begun a good work in confeſſing, but if it go no further the work is ſpoiled; adde we therefore now to it, reformation, let us turn away from thoſe ſins we have drawn up ſo many proteſts againſt, and let us ſhew a practical hatred of what we have verbally renounced.</p>
            <p>Doct. 4. <hi>The b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt outward priviledges in the world, if once they come to be truſted in, are no better then lyes;</hi> ver. 4. <hi>truſt not inlying words, the Temple, &amp;c.</hi> i. e. they have as great and grand a deluſion in them, and as ſurely deceive any that place their confidence upon them as any other deceit in the world whatſoever: they are no better ſhelter, nor will afford any greater ſecurity and ſafeguard to the ſoul then any other vain hiding place; and therefore, they that truſt in them truſt in falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; a lye is that which is ſpoken to deceive the creature: thus when men ſpeak of their priviledges, and reſt on them, they deceive their own ſelves.</p>
            <p>Reaſ. 1. <hi>Becauſe God gives his bleſſing with theſe priviledges but condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally,</hi> i. e. <hi>according to the creatures improvement of them;</hi> if they will make uſe of them aright they are a ſpecial benefit to them, otherwiſe not, 1 Chron: 28: 11: and therefore poſitively and abſolutely to truſt in theſe, and not to carry a reſpect to the condition which is annexed to them, it is to neglect and abuſe Gods order of bleſſing who together with priviledges, promiſeth good to the faithful improver of them, but threatens wrath, and denounceth his judgements againſt the abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of it, and is therefore a great deceit.</p>
            <p>Reaſ. 2. <hi>Becauſe the greater the bleſſing is, if not anſwerably impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, it brings the greater curſe upon the Creature:</hi> Mat. 11. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. that is <hi>Cap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rnaums</hi> ſin, abuſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pel priviledges, and therefore a ſpecial and extraordinary doom is paſt upon them; the greater the mercy is, the more ſadly is God provoked by the abuſing of it, and therefore
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:107003:6"/> who ever eſcape, it's like to fare ill wich ſuch as thoſe. <hi>Am.</hi> 3. 2.</p>
            <p>Uſe 1. <hi>To reprove our carnal confidence in the enjoyment of the means of grace and priviledges of the Goſpel:</hi> you that truſt in your intereſts you have Sabbaths, Sacraments, liberty of neareſt communion with God in his Ordinances, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and hereupon you are ready to think that God loves you, and will not being a ſcourge upon you, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude your ſelves to be exempted from any danger of miſery and deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; let me tell you, <hi>you truſt in lying words, you leane upon ſuch a prop as will certainly fail and deceive you in the latter end.</hi> Conſider, Jer. 9. 25, 26.</p>
            <p>Uſe 2. <hi>To awaken us to bethink our ſelves what uſe it is that we make of the means of grace which we have and enjoy, what good we get by the Ordinances:</hi> think it not enough that we have and enjoy them; you have the temple of the Lord among you, the Word preached from Sabbath to Sabbath, and the Sacraments adminiſtred; theſe are high priviledges, but all the benefit is in the uſe of them, if we have them only to look upon, and boaſt off, and not to improve for our converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to God, and help forward in his ways; they will become a ſnare to us in the end.</p>
            <p>Doct. 5. <hi>'Tis the great ſin of a profeſſing people, in the times of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy, to cover their groſs iniquity under the veil of priviledges and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances.</hi> ver. 8, 9, 10. they thought if they did but come to Gods houſe, and perform a few Ceremonies there, offer ſacrifices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they might take the liberty <hi>to ſteal, murder, ſwear,</hi> and what not; thus we read of that bold and impudent woman, who had not her name for nothing. <hi>Prov.</hi> 7. 14, 15.</p>
            <p>Reaſ. 1. <hi>From their preſumptuous trust in their priviledges, as though God were bound to preſerve his Temple,</hi> he hath no other habitation in the world, and therefore he will never depart from hence, his glory is involved in our preſervation, and will he laugh in our ruine: if he ſhould deſtroy us, his name would be routed out of the earth, and therefore there is no danger that ever we ſhould be cut off, or caſt out; this was their preſumption. <hi>Mich. 3. 11. the Lord is among us, no evil can betide us,</hi> and therefore <hi>they ſteal, judge for reward, wrong the Innocent;</hi> there is no danger.</p>
            <p>Reaſ. 2. <hi>From the ſecret Atheiſm and hypocriſie that is in the heart of vain man.</hi> who thinks God takes no notice of their wickedneſs, but is deceived by their pretended ſervices; men conſider not <hi>that Gods all
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:107003:7"/> all ſeeing eye penetrates into all corners of the earth, and the ſecrets of the heart,</hi> and hence they think they may ſin unſeen. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 8. 12.</p>
            <p>Uſe To <hi>quicken us up to examine our ſelves, whither or no we are not going into Apoſtacy by this;</hi> aske every one his own heart, can we not lanch forth into any ſin, do <hi>violence, ſteale</hi> &amp;c. and yet go &amp; ſtand before the Lord and ſay, <hi>we are delivered to do all theſe abominations: Sin and pray, and pray and ſin again, with as much greedineſs as ever;</hi> come before God and make our confeſſions, tell him a large ſtory of what ſins we have been overtaken withall, and ſeem to beg his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and help againſt it, as though we were willing and deſirous to be rid of it, and yet go away, and ſtrive no more againſt the temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor ſet our ſelves in oppoſition againſt the ſin then we did before; but entertain the ſame with greedineſs, the very next time we meet an opportunity and provocation, be as vain, as paſſionate, <hi>&amp;c</hi> as ever; and when all is done, then come and renſe them over again in few tears and empty confeſſions: and ſo wipe our mouths, and ſay, <hi>what have I done;</hi> if the matter be ſo with us, this is an evidence to us of the depth of hypocriſie in our hearts; well, let us look to our ſelves, we may thus pleaſe our ſelves into a vain hope and ſoul deluſion, but let us know that God and our ſins will find us out.</p>
            <p>Doct. 6. <hi>Hypocritical ſervice is no better then robbery, pretended ſervice to God:</hi> to come reaking from our ſins into the houſe of God to perform a few formal duties, and when we have done, to go thence again with more greedy deſires after it; what is this, but to turn <hi>the houſe of God into a den of Robbers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reaſ. 1. <hi>Becauſe God is hereby robbed of that glory which is due to his Name,</hi> who requires hearty ſervice; which the hypocrite offers up to the Idol of his heart, and not unto God; he gives that glory which is alone due to God, to his <hi>graven Images,</hi> to his own by ends and aims; God requires <hi>the heart,</hi> becauſe he knows that that is the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of all the reſt of the faculties, and it is his due, for he made it; but the hypocrite ſteals the beſt piece of the ſacrifice from God, and is not this Robbery.</p>
            <p>Reaſ. 2. <hi>Becauſe the ſinner hereby robs himſelf of all the good which he ſhould otherwiſe get by his ſervice, if it were done in ſincerity.</hi> Ezek. 14. 7, 8. God hath made great promiſes to ſincerity, in manifold ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions in Scripture, but he denounceth fore woes upon hypocrites, deſtructive deſolation and ruine; ſo that it is time loſt, and rooting our ſelves out from good.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:107003:7"/>
            <p>Uſe <hi>To condemn that ſpirit of hypocriſie which is ready to ſeize upon our hearts,</hi> will you give entertainment to ſecret ſins, and forſake God in your hearts, live in a way and courſe of diſobedience, and yet here come before God in ſolemn and ſerious duties, as though you were good Chriſtians; God looks upon you as no better then <hi>a company of Robbers,</hi> you do at the preſent <hi>rob him of his glory;</hi> but, aſſure your ſelves, he will not be a looſer by you, the time haſtens when he will come and recover his honour out of your hands: and you rob your ſelves of all the good you might get by ſuch opportunities as theſe; oh! if ſuch duties were done in truth and ſincerity, they would bring in a plenteous harveſt; faſting days would be our beſt feaſting days, God would both accept of us, and alſo crown us with admirable bleſſings; but if we will come with an Idol in our hearts, cry out againſt ſuch ſins as we bear an entire love unto, confeſs thoſe evils we never intend to leave off in our courſe, aſſure we our ſelves we ſhall be found the greateſt ſelf Cheaters in the end.</p>
            <p>Doct. 7. <hi>God takes notice of, and will find a time to puniſh the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of a ſinning people;</hi> for both theſe are underſtood in the words<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>ver. 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I behold it, and will requite it:</hi> ſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35. 22, 23.</p>
            <p>Reaſ. <hi>From the Attributes of Omniſcience and Iuſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>God knows all things,</hi> nothing can eſcape his ſight, becauſe his eye is every where. <hi>Pro.</hi> 15. 3. he knows all things, even the ſecrets of the hearts of men, for he made them, every room and corner of them; he therefore keeps a key to them; he muſt needs be Omniſcient, for he is Omnipreſent in all places, by his eſſential preſence; intimate with all things: <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 28.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>He obſerves all things,</hi> and there is reaſon for it, becauſe he admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters the affairs of the whole world; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33. 13, 14, 15. All acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the creatures in the world flow as to their principle from him, and therefore he cannot but take notice of them</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>He will requite, for he is just and cannot but give them their deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> Jer 5. 29. he is the judge of the whole world; and therefore muſt be juſt, he is the higheſt and ſupream judg, beyond whom there is no appeal, and therefore had need be juſt; yea, he is engaged by his Word to do juſtice and execute judgment upon ſinners for their ſins.</p>
            <p>Uſe 1. <hi>To ſhew us how vain a thing it is to go about to deceive God with vain ſervices,</hi> whiles our heart is eſtranged from him; if we had to deal with man like our ſelves, we might eaſily caſt a blind before their
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107003:8"/> eyes, and make them believe ſtrange matters, but God who can in no ways cheat or deceive, though we cover our ſervice with a cloak of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, yet God can tell us whether it be alive or dead; and if we go about ſo to ſerve him, he will make us to know ſooner or later, that he took good notice of them in the day when he comes to ſet our ſins in order before us, and tell us this we did at ſuch a time, and that abomination at another time: <hi>See Pſal. 50. 18. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Uſe 2. <hi>This may certifie the ſinner, that God will take a time to rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon with him,</hi> the alſeeing eye ſees thee, and cannot chuſe but take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of thee, and he will call thee to an account, though he may ſeem to wink at preſent and not to take notice of thy wayes and doings, but to let thee alone; yet I promiſe thee time will be when thou ſhalt know it to thy coſt, that he is not ſuch an one as thou art, nor did ever give his conſent to and approbation of thy wayes and doings: and therefore is there any here that lyes and lives in ſin; deceive not thy own ſoul, but let it awaken thee to look about thee, and make thy peace with God, for otherwiſe <hi>what he hath ſpoken he will performe,</hi> he will not come ſhort of his threatnings any whit more then his pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>miſes, let then that counſel be acceptable. <hi>Am. 4. ult. meet God with Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> before he meet us with his heavy plagues But I come from the Context to the words of the Text: God having counſelled and warned them; the further to awaken and effect their hearts, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them, ſets a lively example before them: in every way ſuiting and anſwering the preſent ſtate of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> he therefore ſets it forth. 1. By the title it once bare, the place <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2. By the evils which were brought upon it: where, 1. The author, God himſelf: what I did. 2. The procuring cauſe, <hi>the wickedneſs of my people Iſrael:</hi> Hence.</p>
            <p>Doct 8. <hi>The example of Gods judgements upon his own people for their ſin and wicked Apoſtacy,</hi> are very uſeful and ſolemn conſiderations for all profeſſors of Religion; the Lord ſends <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to <hi>Shiloh,</hi> and for what end, only to ſee, what he did, and for what, to view his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in their cauſes and effects; to ſee, <hi>i. e.</hi> not only to look on, but to conſider them ſeriouſly, and to make uſe of them to themſelves; and learn ſomething from it for their own conviction; by comparing ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes together.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ground of the truth we may underſtand if we conſider a few pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions:</hi> viz.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>God hath one rule of dealing with all his externally covenanted
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107003:8"/> people in the world,</hi> and that becauſe the covenant with them all runs upon the ſame terms and conditions, for it is a conditional Covenant; in the which there is a promiſe and a threatning, a promiſe annexed to obedience, but a threatning denounced againſt diſobedience. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 19, 20. It is true, God reſerves a ſoveraignty to himſelf as to the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of his dealings with his people in one place or in another; without either infringing his Covenant, or rendring to the creature a Reaſon of that variety; hence, poſſibly patience and mercy may lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger wait upon ſome then others, ſome God may come ſeverely out againſt, for breach of Covenant, and to others he may condeſcend to allow a greater ſpace to repent in, as he pleaſeth, and he does not the leaſt wrong or injury in ſo doing, becauſe he is both ſupream, and hath ends in all his judgements, beyond the capacity of the creatures find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out; but, as to the eſſence of the Covenant, he thus far ſtands po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively and abſolutely engaged to reward obedience, and to puniſh diſobedience; which flows from his everlaſting righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Examples of Gods judgements upon his own people for their ſins, are evident confirmations and teſtimonies that he is a God who proceeds impartially according to his own Rule;</hi> as when Laws are executed according to the tenor of them upon malefactors in the Kingdome; we now know that ſuch Laws were not meer ſcare-crows, made only to fright, but not to hurt, but that there was reality in the Law-makers, and that they were really ſet againſt ſuch evils to ſubvert and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them out, and may teach others to expect what to meet with, in the like ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: ſo, when God puniſheth ſin in his people according to his threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in his word, we now ſee that thoſe threatnings are realities; that his orders and conſtitutions are not bug-bears, but realities, that ſin ſhall not go unpuniſhed. Hence God declares in his word, that he will be known to be God in his judgements. <hi>Exek.</hi> 28. 22 if men will not believe the word, that God will do as he hath ſaid, but preſume upon his mercy and patience; when he takes his rod into his hand, now he is mad, that believs not.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Hence, Examples have matter of precept in them.</hi> Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are documents, there are doctrinal concluſions to be drawn for our inſtruction out of them, hence, we ſhall find God in Scripture cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon his people to look upon Examples. thus, <hi>Luk. 17. 32. 2 Pet.</hi> 2. 4, 5, 6 &amp;c. If God have thus dealt with ſuch a people, we may thence conclude he will deal ſo with thoſe that are ſo qualified, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:107003:9"/> we enjoy the ſame priviledges that Iſrael did, and make no better uſe of them then they made of theirs, we may expect to be viſited as well as they were, and not only may we argue <hi>a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i,</hi> but alſo <hi>ab impa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i,</hi> from the leſſer to the greater; if Iſrael ſo priviledged were not ſpared; how much leſs ſhall we be ſpared, who exceed them in priviledges, if ſinners <hi>under the Law</hi> found no favour, <hi>how much ſorer puniſhment</hi> may ſinners <hi>under the Goſpel</hi> expect: God writes his <hi>ſevere truths</hi> with the <hi>blood</hi> of his <hi>diſobedient Subjects,</hi> and makes their ruinons heaps to proclaim knowledg and counſel to the reſt of the world: <hi>Sodom's aſhes, Shiloh's fire, Ieruſalem's deſolation,</hi> are uſes of inſtruction to the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the Earth.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Examples are of wondrous benefit to give efficacy to Doctrines,</hi> and move upon the affections, and bring them to conſideration, they are uſeful to perſwade; and to move the ſoul to make out after God: <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 6, 7, 8.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Becauſe there is a natural ſympathy between the children of men,</hi> there is a kind of a fellow feeling of ſufferings; when we read only of Doctrines, theſe may reach the underſtanding, but when we read or hear of Examples, humane affection doth as it were repreſent to us the ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e as our own; whereupon the judgements of God, do in the very hearing dwell upon the thoughts, and take upon the heart: when I read the ſtory of <hi>Sodom's overthrow,</hi> me thinks I ſee the Sun riſing in glorious brightneſs, the <hi>Sodomites</hi> ſporting and pleaſing themſelves in their <hi>opulence and ſecurity;</hi> when on a ſudden, me thinks I ſee the heavens covered with thoſe ſable clouds, and hear the great Cannon of heaven thundring down tempeſts upon them, and the ſtreams of fire with horror and dread, till I behold a proud City; on a ſudden be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a <hi>deſolate heap;</hi> when I read <hi>Ieruſale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s hiſtory,</hi> me thinks I ſee the battering Engines placed againſt the walls; the proud enemy climb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the battlements, the feeble and faint-hearted Citizens flying in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to corners, overtaking by the inſulting foe; who without mercy or pity ſheaths his ſword in their bowels; me-thinks I ſee the fire-balls flying too and fro, and the glorious buildings, the work of many years, yeelding to that prevailing and mercyleſs enemy, I hear the cries of raviſhed virgins and bereaved Orphans, yea, I look on till I ſee all Gods threatnings fulfilled, and the glory of the Nations ſtript of all ornament and become a widow, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Becauſe examples come in by the ſenſes, and theſe have a great
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107003:10"/> stroake to move the affections,</hi> and they perſwade the heart of man. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. 51.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Becauſe Examples have an awakening voice in them,</hi> when judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment comes into the world, it carries awe with it, it ſenſibly moves the ſoul to have conſideration; ſuch as theſe are natural influences up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the heart of ſuch as have any remainder of an acting conſcience in them. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Why may not the ſame judgments befall us,</hi> what grounds have we to promiſe our ſelves ſecurity, and immunity from the ſame plagues &amp; miſeries which are upon others.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Hereupon they put the c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eature in mind of its ways and doings,</hi> what they have been; now <hi>conſcience,</hi> if it be not <hi>altogether ſeared and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nummed,</hi> reads the creature a more cloſe and ſevere Lecture then uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, now thoſe ſins that he had before lived in forgetfulneſs came afreſh into his memory.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Hence they are to put the creature into fear of the ſame wrath and terror,</hi> as Scholars, when they ſee their Maſter take the rod in hand, to puniſh offendors; every one preſently conſiders what his faults have been, and if he have been tardy, he ſtands quivering, and quak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, fearfully expecting when his time and turn will come to be called forth.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Now the ſoul is put upon the ſtudy and conſideration how to prevent and eſcape ſevere and like plagues,</hi> now he be-thinks himſelf of making his peace of coming and ſeeking a pardon; for fear leaſt by obſtinacy he bring himſelf to ruine.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Now the creature is alarm'd to Repentance,</hi> he had calls before, but thoſe he regarded not, but now he ſees there is no longer delaying and playing with the threatnings of God, and now, if ever, is the ſoul in a likely way to be reclaimed.</p>
            <p>Uſe <hi>Of counſel and exhortation to us,</hi> in the words of the Text, <hi>go to</hi> Shiloh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the proſecution of which uſe, I ſhall.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Bring you to</hi> Shiloh, <hi>and ſhew you what God did to it, and for what,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Draw ſome uſeful inſtructions from the conſideration of</hi> Shiloh, <hi>and preſs them in a few words of counſel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I. <hi>Then, go to</hi> Shiloh: <hi>and here conſider,</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What <hi>Shiloh</hi> was,</item>
               <item>2. What were their ſins.</item>
               <item>3. Gods judgments on it.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:107003:11"/>
            <p>1. <hi>What</hi> Shiloh <hi>was,</hi> we have it in the words of the Text in two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>It was Gods place:</hi> i. e. <hi>a peculiar place</hi> which he had choſen to himſelf, <hi>his chief place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>It was the place where God ſet his name at the firſt:</hi> i. e. It was the <hi>firſt Tent,</hi> or <hi>Tabernacle</hi> where God ſet up his Ordinances, and called his name upon it, after he had given to <hi>his people Iſrael poſſeſſion of the land of Canaan:</hi> as we ſhall find in <hi>Joſhua</hi> 18. 1. here it was that after the <hi>Arke</hi> had been unſettled for 40 years and upward in the <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs,</hi> God firſt choſe it a fixed place, here was God <hi>worſhiped</hi> firſt-af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had granted a ſettlement to his <hi>people Iſrael.</hi> The Tabernacle was a <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of Gods preſence with his people, <hi>hither the Tribes came up to worſhip,</hi> here it was that God manifeſted his <hi>great glory,</hi> by this it was that God declared Iſrael to be <hi>a peculiar people</hi> to himſelf, ſo that <hi>Shiloh</hi> was not only a part of <hi>God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dwelling place,</hi> for ſo were all the <hi>Tribes,</hi> nor only a habitation of Gods people, for ſo were all other Cities, <hi>Towns</hi> and Villages where Iſrael dwelt, but it was the place of Gods manifeſting himſelf to his peole, <hi>his eſpecial habitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>What was the wickedneſs of</hi> Shiloh; for the Lord ſhews that it was for that, that he did that to it, which he had done; <hi>Text,</hi> now we ſhall ſee the ſin of <hi>Sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>loh,</hi> if we look into 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 12. &amp;c. which was the ſin of the Prieſts in contemning the Ordinances of God, giving an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil example to the people, and enriching themſelves in a way of abuſe of Gods Inſtitutions, and thereby diſcouraging the people from ſerving of God, and of <hi>Eli</hi> in bearing with the wickedneſs, and not ſeverely puniſhing the ſin of his ſons, which God interprets as a preferring them before him. <hi>ver.</hi> 21. &amp;c. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78. 41. to 60. where their horrible ingratitude in forgetting Gods mercies, and woful-Idolatry is declared: this was Iſraels ſin, the Prieſts and people were polluted and defiled, and alienated from God; there was a continuance of Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and ſacrifice, but both abuſe of Ordinances and Idolatry, both in profeſſion and practiſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The judgments of God upon his people Iſrael,</hi> and upon <hi>Shiloh</hi> in particular: we ſhall find recorded in ſcripture, what God did to it; for that is the thing which God would have in eſpecial be minded, look into 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4. 10. 11: where you ſhall find the judgment denounced, and more amply we ſhall read of the execution of it in <hi>Pſal</hi> 78. 59. to 68. where we have deſcribed unto us, the effects of their ſins.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>In alienating of Gods affections from them,</hi> turning of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:107003:11"/> love into hatred. <hi>ver.</hi> 59. God had formerly loved Iſrael, they were to him a choice people, tender as the apple of ones eye, tenderly taken care for, and foſtered by him, protected from evils, dandled in the lap of his providence, and ſingularly reſpected by him; as we ſhall find amply related to us in <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 7, &amp;c. But now his heart was hardned againſt them, and his former love turned into abhorrence and deteſtation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The conſequents following upon this,</hi> or the tokens whereby God ſignified and expreſſed his diſpleaſure unto them, which are.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>God departed and forſook them,</hi> even his own houſe, not only the other Cities, of Iſrael, but even his own tent at <hi>Shiloh, ver.</hi> 60.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>When God had left them, all miſeries followed,</hi> ver. 61. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> their crown was taken from their head, and their enemies which formerly were tributary to them, now lord it over them, yea, an univerſal deluge of miſeries came upon them, as you may there read. Thus you ſee <hi>Shiloh,</hi> once choſen by God, where he ſet up his Ordinances, made his name to dwell, and ſhone forth in his wonderful glory: forſaken by God, and buryed in its own ruines, altogether diſowned and refuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as a place of abhorrence and contempt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Let us conſider what we may learn at</hi> Shiloh, obſerve here even from the conſideration of this example.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That God hath no where on earth ſo engaged himſelf and his preſence, but that ſin may drive him away:</hi> where was his name greater then at <hi>Shiloh;</hi> there was the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> there was the Prieſts and Levites ſerving, there were daily morning and evening ſacrifices, thither came the tribes yearly to appear before God, there were the ſeals of Gods Covenant, yet is <hi>Shiloh</hi> deſerted and deſtroyed; <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> may alſo witneſs this truth, the once dwelling place of God, where the <hi>Temple</hi> was, the place whereof God had ſaid, this is my reſt for ever, here will I dwell, for I have deſired it. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132. 14. but now behold it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted and twice made the ſubject of Gods fury, and not ſo much as the ruines of it left to teſtifie what it was, <hi>a ſtone not to be found upon a ſtone;</hi> hence therefore learn we not to promiſe our ſelves ſecurity if we be found in the ways of ſin, whatſoever engagement and covenant God may ſeem to ſtand bound in unto us, God knows how to keep up his glory in the world, though we be ruinated, he can keep up a Church in the world, though we be left deſolate; the ſtones of the field, if he but ſpeak the word, ſhall riſe up children of <hi>Abraham;</hi> the remoteſt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:107003:12"/> ends of the earth ſhall come in, and the children of the Kingdom ſhall be thruſt out; let not this therefore be your reſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That Sion affords no more ſecurity to ſinners then</hi> Sodom, Shiloh is as dangerous a place to ſin in, as any in the world; if a people in covenant with God, be found rebellious, he will ſpare them no more then any other people, nay he will begin with them. <hi>Am. 3. 2. judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall begin at his houſe;</hi> Shilohs ruines are a memorial of this, and declare how vain it is to take ſanctuary in the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> and ſhreud our ſelves from judgment under pretence of Gods covenant; <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſmarted dearly for this ſin, if <hi>Ioab</hi> be a man of death, it avails him not to take hold of the <hi>horns of the Altar:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Learn we therefore from hence, to beware to our ſelves, how we make bold to ſin, and think the Covenant ſhall ſave us; if God find us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious, &amp; bold ſinners, though we ſhould hide our ſelves in the <hi>Temple,</hi> and take refuge under the pretended ſhadow of Gods promiſes of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and love to us, God will yet find us out, and will not ſpare us; whatever they plead for themſelves. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 21, 22. yet Chriſts anſwer ſtill is, <hi>I know you not;</hi> I tell thee, when God ſhall come forth to execute his judgements upon ſinners, thy church memberſhip, thy priviledges ſhall not ſave thee, God will no more regard thee for all this then if thou wert an <hi>Indian;</hi> except it be to puniſh thee the more, becauſe thy ſins have therein been greater, and more hainous: if ſuch pleas could have prevailed, who could have pleaded more then <hi>Shiloh?</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>General Apoſtacy makes way for general calamity,</hi> learn this in <hi>Shiloh;</hi> the Prieſts violated Gods Ordinances, and the people they provoked him with their Idols, and then ſee the effects. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4. 10, 11. Iſrael is ſmitten, 30000 <hi>ſlain,</hi> the Ark loſt, <hi>the Prieſts ſlain,</hi> read this alſo in <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> 2 Chron. 36. 15, 16, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> hence therefore what grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter requeſt can we leave with God this day, than this, that he would prevent our general decay in grace, and to that end, that he would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the fallen, prevent the backſliding, and ſettle hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> own, that mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy may be ſettled among us; pray for rulers in Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, that they may do right, and give good examples, and for all the body of people, that ſin do not grow and encreaſe among them; if once we ſee a ſpirit of prevailing corruption ſpreading it ſelf among us, we may read leading ſymptomes of deſtruction &amp; miſery, &amp; therefore may be rouſed up to ply the throne of grace, that ſuch ſad cauſes may be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:107003:12"/> removed, and ſo our eyes may not ſee the natural direfull effects that flow from them,</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Lenetie in Rulers, brings ruine upon a people,</hi> whether in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth or in Churches: Rulers may be good men in themſelves, ſo was <hi>Eli,</hi> but if they give way to ſinfull forbearance in the executing of Juſtice according to the will of God, they are not occaſions onely, but leading cauſes to the undoing of a people, becauſe ſuch a ſpirit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimates wicked ſpirits, and makes them bold to do perverſely upon preſumption of a pardon, or to be paſt by with ſome gentle reproof; God chargeth <hi>Shiloh's</hi> deſtruction upon <hi>Eli,</hi> who was <hi>Judg in Iſrael,</hi> and when his Sons the <hi>Prieſts</hi> did wickedly, he connives ſo far, as only to rebuke them, who being gotten beyond remorſe or ſenſe of reproof abuſed their Fathers patience, to add to their Rebellion; therefore muſt <hi>Shiloh be laid waſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence therefore, let this teach us to pray unto God, to <hi>put a Spirit into our Rulers, Zealous againſt Sin,</hi> eſpecially in theſe times of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing iniquity; and let us, in our place incourage them in ſo doing, by rejoycing in acts of Juſtice and ſeverity, againſt ſuch evils as grow and thrive among us: Pray that they may not reſpect perſons, nor en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage ſome in ſin, by ſparing others; eſpecially remembring, that as long as ſuch a ſpirit is in Rulers, what ever ſins there be in a people, there are ſtill ſome to <hi>ſtand in the Gap.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>The greateſt Mercys abuſed by ſin, give God the higheſt provocation.</hi> God recounts what he had done for them, and what they had done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, <hi>Iſrael ſinned greivouſly,</hi> after ſuch and ſuch favours, and when <hi>God heard this,</hi> when this was the report brought him of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement that they had made of all his mercyes, this brings them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to abhorrence: and good reaſon there is for it, for every mercy is an <hi>obligation laid upon the creature to obedience;</hi> hence the greater the mercy is, the ſtronger tye lyes upon the creature; to ſin therefore againſt <hi>mercy, grace,</hi> and <hi>ſpeciall mercyes,</hi> is to break Gods ſtrong <hi>cord of Love,</hi> then which, what greater provocation can there be: Conſider <hi>David &amp; Hanu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 2 Sam.</hi> 10. Ingratitude in return for friendſhip, is the moſt hard to bear of any thing. Aske we then our own hearts, what uſe we have made of all thoſe great mercies which our God hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon us: great favours we have had, equal with thoſe he had ſhewed to his people at Shiloh; yea, if all things be conſidered, we may well ſay, Superiour unto them, in as much as the dayes of the Goſpel
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:107003:13"/> afford far greater light, then the dayes of the <hi>Law</hi> did; and have we remembred what God hath done for us? ſo as to make our returns unto him; hath he had his <hi>tribute of thankefull Obedience?</hi> have we lived up to our enjoyments? have we been <hi>ſingular in holineſs?</hi> as we have been ſingular in the <hi>means of holineſs;</hi> or have we not rather grown vain and looſe, and prophane? deſpiſing of the meanes, and hardening our hearts againſt the <hi>Counſels of God?</hi> if it be ſo with us, <hi>Go to Shiloh,</hi> and tremble.</p>
            <p n="6">6: A People forſaken of God are in the road way to all miſery: we read, God forſakes his Tent <hi>which was in Shiloh,</hi> and what follows, <hi>but ruine and waſte, and an univerſal deluge of deſtruction:</hi> all woes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low when he is gone, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 9. 12. and reaſon there is for it, for his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour is the life of a people, his protection is their only defence; well may it therefore be ſaid of a people, deſerted by God, their rock hath ſold them into the hands of miſery: fear we therefore to provoak God to leave us. Conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>All our bleſſings are in his hand, he holds us at his diſpoſe, if any people in the World, then to be ſure</hi> we are at Gods proviſion, who have no ſtore but what his yearly bleſſing brings in unto us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Sin will provoke him to leave us,</hi> for he is a <hi>God of purer eyes then to behold iniquity, i. e.</hi> with love, liking or approbation; his holineſs engageth him to manifeſt ſignal diſcoveries of the contrariety which he hath againſt ſin.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>If when he repoves our ſins, we harden our ſelves in them, it is a ſure ſigne that he is forſakeing of us,</hi> Jer. 7. 28. Have we therefore given to God any provocation to unſettle himſelfe, an think of a removall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from us: Oh let our repentance fetch him back and ſettle him.</p>
            <p>Laſtly. <hi>It is a fearfull thing to fall into the hands of the Living God:</hi> The Charracters of Gods wrath, &amp; impreſſions of his Judgements re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining upon <hi>Shiloh,</hi> teach us this Leſſon: If God come once to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horr a people for their ſins, and fall upon them in his Judgments; he meets them not as a man, but gives them a <hi>Divine ſtroak;</hi> if he be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, his very countenance is terrible and amazing. <hi>Pſal. 18. 8 &amp;c. Hab.</hi> 3. what is he then, when he poures out his diſpleaſure: Labour wee then from the example of <hi>Shiloh,</hi> to <hi>fear and dread</hi> provoaking the great God to wrath againſt us: what ever cauſes moving to this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, are in Gods goodneſs removed away from us, yet the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of our ſins is matter ſufficient to humble us before God this day;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:107003:13"/> Better it is for us to bow our ſelves before him, leſt he break us in pieces: and therefore let it be our great endeavour to meet God in the way by Repentance, before he come home to us in wrath, and fall upon us in his ſore diſpleaſure; let that be the great practical leſſon that we learn at <hi>Shiloh.</hi> For motive:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider, <hi>God will not bear with ſin, let him find it where he will:</hi> He is no reſpecter of perſons, <hi>circumciſed, or uncircumciſed, if uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed in heart:</hi> Jer 9. 25<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 26. if he find it in Church, or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, in Rulers, or Subjects; where he finds it, he will puniſh it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>God is yet willing to be met with Repentance,</hi> we have many ſigns and tokens of Gods deſire rather that we ſhould live then dye, hence hath he drawn out his long ſuffering to ſo long a thread as he hath done; by following with counſels, and piece-mealing out his judgments.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>There is all Reaſon we ſhould acknowledge and repent,</hi> we are not able to give a good Reaſon, only we have ſinned againſt him, that was unreaſonable: <hi>Ier.</hi> 2 5. and if ſo, then needs muſt it be Rational, that we ſhould ſee the evil, and take the ſhame to our ſelves of ſuch unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable doings.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>If God once take us in hand, he will be known, and make us to know too, how ſad and miſerable a thing it is for us to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>force him to cut us off, do we provoke him to jealouſie,</hi> do we not rather provoke our own fouls to ruine: Oh remember! remember! if we have made him our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary by ſin, he is yet in the way, though he may be coming in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet he waits to be gracious he hath waited long, <hi>turn not his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience into fury,</hi> why ſhould we be made like unto <hi>Shiloh:</hi> God is mercifull, true, but he is juſt too, and he can make his wrath known, ask <hi>Shiloh</hi> elſe, and they can tell you a ſad ſtory of it: Look on <hi>Shiloh,</hi> Look on <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> look on the multitude of <hi>deſolate Churches,</hi> and take warning by theſe to fall down before God, to receive his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs; <hi>if you be wiſe, be wiſe for your ſelves;</hi> turn to him, <hi>for why ſhould ye dye?</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:107003:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:107003:14"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ISAIAH. 26. 9.</bibl>
               <q>When thy Judgements are in the Earth, the Inhabitants of the World will learn Righteouſneſs.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Chapter is a Song, Celebrating <hi>the Prayſes of God,</hi> in his Judgments on his Enemies, and favours to his People; and is full of Spirituall matter.</p>
            <p>The Song is appointed to be Sung by <hi>the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full at their deliverance from the Babiloniſh Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity.</hi> In this 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>verſe.</hi> The Church Declares;</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Her own Frame under the</hi> Judgements of God: namely an <hi>Earneſt and early Deſire</hi> after him: <hi>In the night,</hi> Signifies in the darke and gloomy <hi>times of affliction,</hi> when they were under the <hi>Tyranny and Captivity</hi> of the Enemy, ſhut up as it were in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>What ſhould be the Frame of all that<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſee or hear of Gods ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible doings in the world,</hi> it ſhould teach them <hi>Righteouſneſs:</hi> of which latter we may at this ſeaſon make ſome improvement; and a little to open the Words.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:107003:15"/>
            <p>[<hi>When thy Judgments:, &amp;c.</hi>] Judgments are Acts of Divine <hi>Iuſtice, Vindicative,</hi> all Gods diſpenſations to the creature, are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led either acts of <hi>Mercy</hi> or <hi>juſtice;</hi> Not as if there were a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction in theſe two; God is Juſt where he is Mercifull, <hi>i. e.</hi> his being mercifull doth not infringe or wrong his juſtice at all: and where God is Juſt, he is Mercifull alſo, in this world; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his juſtice is here diſpenſed with moderation; though the time be comeing when he will execute juſtice without mercy:</p>
            <p>But wherein any act of <hi>Divine Providence,</hi> one of theſe Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes is more viſible to the creature then the other, thence it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives its Denomination.</p>
            <p>Judgments, <hi>are Judicial acts of Gods Senerity in the World, wherein he declares himſelfe to be ſet against ſin or ſinners;</hi> Some tranſlate it <hi>Chaſtizements:</hi> Judgment ſometimes intend <hi>proper acts of Revenging juſtice;</hi> when God comes forth to right himſelfe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his enemies, in their wonderfull deſtruction: Sometimes <hi>ſevere afflictions,</hi> though intended for the amendment of thoſe who ſuffer them: the word ſignifies properly, <hi>a doing right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>[<hi>Righteouſneſs</hi>] The word ſignifies <hi>Truth and Equity:</hi> it is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes in Scripture reſtrained to <hi>ſecond Table dutyes,</hi> and then it is diſtinguiſhed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> from <hi>Holyneſs,</hi> which referrs to <hi>firſt Table dutyes,</hi> but here, as in many other places, it is uſed more largely, to ſignifie a <hi>reformation of Life,</hi> and univerſal <hi>Anaſtaſy,</hi> or <hi>Reclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> from their former ſinfull courſes.</p>
            <p>[<hi>Will learne</hi>] This is ſpoken as if ſuch an effect ſhould come to paſs in all that ſhould ſee and hear of Gods judgements; for the Scripture ſpeaks of ſome, that when Gods hand was upon them, they ſinned yet more: thus <hi>Ahaz:</hi> 2 Chron. 28. 22. but it is ſpoken either,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>By way of Preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mption,</hi> as if they ſhould ſay, <hi>ſurely they will learn righteouſneſs.</hi> or,</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:107003:15"/>2. <hi>Expreſſing what ought to be,</hi> as if it would be; ſuch a thing ſhould be, and if men were in a right frame, it would be: the meaning is, that there is matter enough in Gods judgements to awaken the world to righteouſneſs. Hence,</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>The Judgements of God in the World carry along with them an univerſal awakening call to Righteouſneſs.</hi> When God comes forth rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his <hi>fiery Chariot,</hi> and diſpenſeth terrible things among the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men, it ſends forth a loud cry to the world to reform and amend their ways. By way of Explication, Conſider a few things.</p>
            <p>Firſt. <hi>All judgements are of God,</hi> it's ſaid thy judgements, they come from him: here obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Some judgements are more immediate,</hi> they come by an<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> unſeen hand and in an unknow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> way, we ſee the effects, but are not able to track them in their cauſes; of ſuch as theſe, even an <hi>Egyptian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gician</hi> muſt ſay, <hi>lo the finger of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Other judgements come mediately by the mediation or efficiency of Inſtruments,</hi> ſecond cauſes are the next occaſion of them, and theſe are either.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Devils, who have a great ſtroake in many effects of providence,</hi> they come by Divine permiſſion, God giving them a licenſe, ſo far as he ſees meet for his own ends; and ſometimes they come with a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from God on his errands, who ſhall for us <hi>perſwade</hi> Ahab <hi>to go to</hi> Ramoth Gilead <hi>and fall?</hi> I, ſaith the Devills, <hi>go, ſaith God, and proſper,</hi> 1 Kings 22. 20. &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Men, who are many times the meanes of bringing ſore and ſad calamities upon their fellow creatures,</hi> being uſed and improved by God to that end, by Warrs, and deſolations that follow ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, thus God uſed the <hi>Philiſtins, Syrians, Aſſyrians</hi> &amp;c. to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict Iſrael <hi>and</hi> Judah.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Bruit beaſts and unreaſonable creatures,</hi> who ſerve their great Lord againſt man, when he rebells againſt God, which otherwiſe ſhould have been ſubſervient to him: thus the <hi>fiery Serpents in the wilderneſs,</hi> the <hi>two ſhee Bears,</hi> to tear in peeces the mocking chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, thus <hi>Locuſts, Caterpillers, Palmer wormes</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Elements, Starrs, Rivers, Vapours, Rain, Drought</hi> &amp;c. the <hi>Starrs fought in their courſe againſt Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>era,</hi> the <hi>brook Kiſhon ſwept<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> them away</hi> Judg 5.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:107003:16"/>
            <p>By all theſe meanes God may bring ſevere puniſhments upon the creture for his ſin: but all theſe are from God, they are his Judgments, and come of his errand. This appears;</p>
            <p n="1">1. From <hi>the Supream Efficiency of God;</hi> all creatures move as they are moved by him: in the matter of the action, if he give not his <hi>Efficiency,</hi> they can do nothing at all: <hi>in him we live, mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and have our being:</hi> his Efficiency is the firſt mover, he is as it were the firſt wheel of the great clock of the world, or the ſpring of this watch: Second beings have an operation, but it hath an abſolute dependence upon his Co-operation, ſo that if ſo much as a <hi>dog wag his tongue</hi> againſt us, there is not only <hi>Divine permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> in it, but <hi>Divin Efficiency</hi> alſo.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From <hi>his Providential Ordering of all the affaires of the world:</hi> God <hi>ſits King upon the flood</hi> Pſal. 29. 10. He is Soveraign diſpoſet of all things, and therefore good and evill comes from him, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be that doth it. <hi>Amos</hi> 3. 6. God ſaith David, <hi>bid Shemei curſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe <hi>Prayer to God hath been the meanes of turning aſide judgment, yea even then when Inſtruments have done their worſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> the people of God in their diſtreſs. have but acquainted God with it, and ſought him in the caſe, and the buiſineſs hath been done: thus <hi>David</hi> prayes to God to <hi>turn the counſell of Achitophel into fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and its done; and he who formerly was looked upon to ſpeak <hi>Oracles,</hi> is now diſregarded: <hi>Hezekiah</hi> doth tell, go into the the houſe of God, and ſpread <hi>Rabſhekah's raling letter</hi> before him and leaves the caſe with him; and the next newes is, an Angel is ſent from hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, who ſlayes in one night <hi>an hundred, fourſcore</hi> and <hi>five</hi> thouſand of his enemies, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 19. 35. Hence we have the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es confidence in Gods protection, enabling them to <hi>ſound a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge</hi> to their enemies to do their worſt againſt them. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8. 9, 10. there is their boldneſs, <hi>God is with us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly. <hi>All thoſe acts of Divine Providence, wherein God diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers his ſeverity in any degree againſt ſin,</hi> are properly the Judgments of God: wherever God layes his heavy hand upon a people: <hi>whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. In Revenging himſelf upon his enemies, by cutting them off, or ſorely viſiting them.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:107003:16"/>2. In Puniſhments and Chaſtiſements upon his people, when for their amendment he brings diſappointments and afflictions upon them, for in both theſe God doth 1. Shew himſelf ſet againſt ſin: 2. Do right.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Judgements</hi> are either</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Mere ordinary</hi> diſpenſations of Divine Providence, ſuch as are more common; as the uſual afflictions which God brings upon any in way of penalty, <hi>viz.</hi> Sickneſſes, Croſſes, Loſſes, Poverty, D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſgrace, Rain, Famine, Peſtilence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> theſe are Gods uſual Scourges. Or</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>More extraordinary,</hi> when ſome remarkable providence that is not uſual doth befall any, ſuch Caſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ties <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are more rare and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frequent, ſuch as Poſſeſſion by Devils, Deaths by Thunder and Ligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and the like.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Juagements</hi> are either</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Private and Perſonal,</hi> when God ſhews his ſeverity upon perſons or families, who are ſingled out from others to be the ſubjects of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ction. Or</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>General and Epidemical Viſitations,</hi> when God comes and brings a ſcourge upon a Country or a People.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>Judgements</hi> are either</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Outward,</hi> when the next and immediate ſubject they ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> upon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is mens Bodies or Eſtates, and damnifie them in either. Or</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Spiritual,</hi> when they ſeize upon mens Souls and Spirits; as Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions, Deſperations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I mention theſe diſtinctions, partly th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> we may be the better directed to a careful obſervance, that we may diſcover God coming in his ſeveral awful diſpenſations upon us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and partly becauſe we may improve ſome of them in the Application<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, All <hi>Judgements</hi> whatſoever, and in what way ſoever they come, are <hi>Doctrinal,</hi> they bring inſtruction and teaching along with them, to thoſe that either ſee or hear of them: they are ſpeaking Providences.</p>
            <p>Here conſider, 1. That they are Doctrinal. 2. How far they are ſo.</p>
            <p>I. <hi>That all Judgements are Doctrinal,</hi> will appear, if we conſider,</p>
            <p>Firſt, that Judgements in relation to the ſubject of them, are acts of the Soveraign Juſtice of God. There are two things in this Poſition.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are <hi>Acts of Juſtice,</hi> becauſe God viſits none beyond their ſins deſert: what-ever Gods dealing be to any, he will vindicate him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:107003:17"/> ſelf that he doth them no wrong, there is ſin enough in the creature to make him to <hi>juſtifie God when he judgeth,</hi> Pſal. 51. 3, 4. Job 40. 4, 5.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are <hi>Acts of Soveraign Juſtice:</hi> which appears, becauſe God doth not viſit all alike in the world, whoſe ſins are alike, but picks and chuſeth as he ſees meet, ſome to be monuments of his ſeverity, whiles others are left. Gods Soveraignty herein appears, becauſe he follows no other Rule but his <hi>own pleaſure,</hi> in making choice whom to diſpenſe Judgements, and whom to leave; ſo that ſometimes he leaves, and lets alone, ſuch as have been greater ſinners in many ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravating reſpects, whiles he takes others that have not been ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious: and therefore our Saviour Chriſt, to them enquiring about <hi>the man born blinde,</hi> removes the cauſe from them to Gods Soveraignty, <hi>Joh.</hi> 9. 2, 3.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they naturally teach theſe leſſons:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That God is a juſt God, that he is ſet againſt ſin, and will not alwayes bear with ſinners: dayes of patience make ſinners forget, yea Atheiſtically think God is not holy and juſt; but he is known in his Judgements, theſe are beginning diſcoveries before the great and general Aſſizes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That God will ſooner or later be revenged upon ſinners: every monument of Divine Reve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge lectures out what others may look for and expect at the hands of God. Gods Judgements declare that ſin ſhall not alwayes go unpuniſhed, that though there be a day of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance, yet there ſhall alſo be a day wherein they ſhall receive their wages.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That there ſhall be a great Day of Judgement: for if ſome ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners are here taken, and others in this world forborn, according to the pleaſure of Gods Soveraign will, this ſhews that there muſt be another day above and beſides all theſe Judgement-dayes, wherein God ſits upon ſome ſinners in this world.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That there is no ſecurity in a ſtate of ſin, though we are not ſuch notorious ſinners as others, yet are we under ſin; we lye open and liable to the Judgements of God, and may as ſoon as others be made monuments of it. It is no cloak to ſay, I am not as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad as ſuch and ſuch: Art thou out from the promiſe of Gods ſpecial grace? thou art every day open to Judgement.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That there is no ſafety but in making our peace with God: if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>od ſway the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>epter, and act his own pleaſure upon ſinners, we are
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:107003:17"/> in a dangerous ſtate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as long as we are not agreed with him, but have him for our adverſary. And hence the concluſion is to teach men righteouſneſs, to forſake thoſe ſins that are provoking to God, and lay hold upon him in a way of true Repentance, in time, for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, leſt we alſo be made monuments of his wrath: this is the voice of all the Judgements of God which they ſpeak to the world.</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>How far they are Doctrinal:</hi> This is conſiderable, either in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Judgements</hi> themſelves. All Judgements ſerve to teach, they have a voice in them, but ſome cry louder then others. There is a voice in common calamities and diſappointments, but a louder voice in extraordinary Judgements; Natural cauſes bring awful Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but more aw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ul when they are Preternatural; every ſickneſs and diſeaſe, every croſs and loſs ſpeaks, but when God goes out of the ordinary path, here is a more awakening Call. In a word, the more ſtupendious and admirable the Providence is, the louder is the voice of God, and more clear to be heard, for then <hi>the Lion roars, Amos</hi> 38.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Of the <hi>Places</hi> wherein they are:</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) <hi>Judgements remote</hi> have a voice to us, let them be never ſo far off, if we have any cognizance of them, for the Text limits it to no narrower bounds then the World.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) But <hi>Judgements near</hi> are more loud: when a fire is in our neighbours houſe, it then bids us to look about us to ſecure our own.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) But <hi>Judgements at h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me</hi> are moſt loud of all, in our Town, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in our Families, for then God eries among us, yea the ſtroke of his Rod is upon us, and therefore its high time for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>very one to ſee to himſelf.</p>
            <p>3. In reſpect of Senſes:</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) <hi>Judgements heard of</hi> are awful, for this is a great ſenſe of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline. But</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) <hi>Judgements ſeen and felt</hi> are more dreadful and awakening; and the Reaſon is, Becauſe theſe S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſes are more intelligent, and leſs fallacious: we may queſtion the truth of reports, but what we <hi>ſee</hi> and <hi>feel</hi> we have leſs cauſe to ſuſpect. If any Senſe can inform with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>allacy, it is theſe: as alſo theſe are the moſt affecting Senſes, <hi>The eye affects the heart,</hi> much more then when the hand of God lyes heavy upon a perſon.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:107003:18"/>
            <p>Seventhly, It is the will and command of God that his Judgements ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> men righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. Becauſe he ſingles out ſome to ſhew his judgements upon, and takes not all ſinners as he might do: this ſhews that God would have men improve this day of his patience to Repentance. God hath Pleas enough againſt others, and might have executed his wrath on them, but when he does not, he ſhews that he would have others to get good by it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. Becauſe God in his Word calls men to conſider and obſerve his Judgements; he declares it to be his will, that when he viſits any in ſeverity for their ſins, <hi>All Iſrael ſhould hear, and fear, and do no more ſo.</hi> When God would reclaim <hi>Judah</hi> from their vain confidence, and awaken them to repentance, he ſends them to <hi>Shiloh,</hi> to ſee what waſtes and deſolations he had there made, <hi>Jer.</hi> 7. 12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 3. Becauſe none of Gods Providences are in vain, God doth nothing in the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld to no purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 4. Becauſe God does<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by hsi awakening Judgements teach them he intends good to: <hi>David</hi> profeſſeth, <hi>Thy judgements make me afraid,</hi> i. e. afraid to ſin, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>raid to be licentious and remiſs in my life and wayes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 5. Becauſe God doth charge the neglect of this duty upon <hi>Judah</hi> as a great, grievous, and provoking ſin: when he had executed his judgements upon her ſiſter <hi>Aholah (Iſrael,</hi> the Ten Tribes) that <hi>Aholi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ah (Judah</hi>) held on her own old courſes of ſin, and was no whit affected therewithall, nor did by it learn to amend, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> I. Of <hi>Information</hi> of our judgements in divers things<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That Afflictions and Calamities are not by caſualty, they are Gods Judgement<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, ordered and fore-determined by him; not a Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row falls to the ground without him: and therefore let it teach us not to ſlight them, or look upon them in a negligent manner, as things that come promiſcuouſly, and imprudently to paſs, but by the wiſe diſpoſal of God. See God in all that falls out in the world, and adore him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it is our duty to look beyond Inſtruments in every Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that befalls us. It is true, Inſtruments are ſome of them ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ional, ſome are irrational; and hence ſome Inſtruments may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lame-worthy, may juſtly be accuſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and if God give opportunity, may in a way of Equity be proceede<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> againſt: but we muſt not reſt in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:107003:18"/> the malice of Inſtruments, but look <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urther, and ſee the hand of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> its a fooliſh dog that runs after the ſtone, and mindes not the hand that threw it. If we look upon the moſt rational Inſtruments, as they be in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ands of God, and conſider them as under his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign diſpoſal, they are no more then as an Ax or K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ife, or any other inſtrument in the hands of a man: <hi>The Aſſyrian <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y rod</hi> Iſa. 10. 5. Hence God is nevertheleſs to be ſeen for the malice or ſpight of the creature, becauſe he improves even <hi>the wrath of man to his praiſe, and the remainder of wrath he reſtrains.</hi> Learn we hence in all the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that befall us, not ſo much to ſay what means the inſtrument, but what provokes God, <hi>though Syrian before and Philiſtim behinde, yet let Iſrael return to God that ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ites him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That times wherein God brings his Judgements among a people, are ſolemntimes, and ought to be entertained with ſolemnity; they are times of ſerious conſideration, <hi>Hag.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 5. and humiliation. God when he viſits a people in Judgement, bids <hi>blow the trumpet, call a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn aſſembly, return to the Lord with weeping, wailing, and lamentation, Joel</hi> 2. 1, 2, 13. We are not therefore before God this day in this ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn duty, uncalled for<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That no perſon that ſees or hears of Gods Judgements is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concerned: if he be an inhabitant of this world, there is a voice to him. Learn we therefore to have a care of diſintereſting our ſelves, or ſaying, What relation hath this or that to me?</p>
            <p n="5">5. That the more of Gods Judgements have been among a people, the more God will have againſt them, if they repent not; God will have deſpiſed Judgements to lay to their charge: it will be an heavy aggravation of ſuch a peoples ſin, that they have not onely had and enjoyed Gods Ordinances among them, but thoſe backed with his Truth-confirming Providences, ſpeaking once and again, ſpeaking to many Senſes at once, and yet they have got nothing by them; this is an argument of an exceeding hard heart. Gods Judgements in this world, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we repent not, will not mitigate but increaſe our judgements and woes in another.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> II. For <hi>Reproof.</hi> And here let me come home in this Uſe an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the next, to the caſe and providence which hath oc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſioned this dayes ſolemnity, the awful Judgement of God that is among us: and the Reproof is, That the Judgements of God that have befallen us, and in particular this great Judgement, is no more nor better made
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:107003:19"/> uſe of by us then it is. Let this conſideration have its weight in hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling us this day before God.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We may all chide with our own hearts, that we are no more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with it, that there is ſo much ice and coldneſs in us, that our affections are ſcarce warmed with ſuch a providence; we may lay our hands upon our mouthes, and be angry with our ſelves, that we finde ſuch a chilneſs upon our affections. But</p>
            <p n="2">2. Particularly, thoſe deſerve a Reproof,</p>
            <p>Firſt, That make all their application to thoſe whom the Judgement is upon: Oh the ſpirit of cenſure that is in too many, and there they reſt; Surely there is ſome ſpecial reaſon, ſome more then ordinary provocation, why elſe is God come out upon that Family, rather then upon any other Family? I do not here ſpeak to make thoſe whom the Judgement nextly concerns, to be regardleſs of Gods hand upon them; no, let them know that God calls them into the School of Search, and would have them in particular try what is the meaning of his ſo ſevere coming out againſt them, that they may learn to ſit in ſilence, and juſtifie him: But I ſpeak to others, who are apt to judge of perſons by providences, though Scripture teacheth us that <hi>all things fall out alike unto all.</hi> And therefore let ſuch conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. This practice is contrary to our Saviours precept, who admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth others by ſuch providences to learn this leſſon, that <hi>except they repent, they ſhall likewiſe periſh,</hi> Luke 13. 2, 3. it ſeems perſonal appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation ſuits better, its the wiſeſt way to bring all things home to our own Souls; that might be profitable to us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This is to forget our own ſinfulneſs: whiles we judge and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure others, we do tacitly juſtifie our ſelves, and think our ſelves bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then others; we interpret our merit rather then Gods mercy to be the diſtinguiſhing cauſe: and is not this to lift up our ſelves too high?</p>
            <p n="3">3. This is to forget divine Soveraignty: God all this while is not adored by us in his Supreme uncontrolable diſpoſal which he hath of all creatures, to lay his hand where he pleaſeth, without giving ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to the creature. Conſider well with thy ſelf, and it may be thou haſt been ten times a greater ſinner, if all the circumſtances of aggravation were well pondered and weighed, but God for ends beſt known to himſelf hath thus dealt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This is the way to rob God of the glory of his goodneſs to thee
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:107003:19"/> in preſerving thee from this ſad Calamity, whereas if thou reflect in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, thou mighteſt ſee ſo much of provocation in thy own heart, and ſo many grievous obliquities and wanderings, that it would ſet thee into a rapture of admiration, at the unſpeakable favour which appears in thy preſervation, who mighteſt have been choſen in the room of this perſon, to have been hung up as a ſign, and a wonder, and an aſtoniſhment, for others with ſad hearts to have looked upon.</p>
            <p n="5">5. This is not to learn Righteouſneſs; for that is onely by draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing concluſions home to our ſelves, and making the caſe our own: yea, this is a way to harden our hearts in wickedneſs. Let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore learn to make a better uſe of this tremendous Providence.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Thoſe that look not beyond Inſtruments. There is a great deal of enquiry made about the Devils agency, and raiſing of Spirits againſt ſuch as we are ready to think may be his ſubſervient actors in this caſe, but how many are there that look no further. Conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. This is to forget the Supremacy of Divine Providence; we do not remember that God ſits and rules over Men and Devils, and that in ſuch an uncontrolable manner, that Earth and Hell cannot move to any act upon the creature, unleſs he permit them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It tends to hinder the right efficacy of this Judgement upon the Soul; for it raiſeth; and humbles not the Soul of the creature: it is the way to provocation and exaſperation, to bitterneſs and rage, from the conſideration of the virulency of the enemy, and that we have not deſerved it at their hands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereas if we looked beyond theſe, to God the prime Efficient, it would teach us ſilence, and holy ſubmiſſion: <hi>I was dumb,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>becauſe thou didſt it,</hi> Pſal. 39. 9.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Thoſe that look upon the Providence with ſlighty and common affections, whoſe hearts are not awed by it, but look upon it as a matter of little or no concernment, are as jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>und, as vain, as light, as frothy as ever they were: there are too many of theſe. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. This argues that God is not feared by ſuch hearts, thoſe that fear not God in his Judgements, eſpecially in ſuch Judgements, may well be thought not to fear him at all. Aſſure thy ſelf if this Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, ſo ſolemn, have left no impreſſion upon thee, thou haſt a heart as hard as a rock.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is impoſſible that ſuch ſhould learn Righteouſneſs: the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:107003:20"/> Affections are the feet of the Soul, if theſe move not, there is little good to be hoped for in ſuch an one, and therefore never look that ſuch ſhould get any good by it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Thoſe that have loſt their Affections: it may be many were at the firſt, at the newneſs and ſtrangeneſs of the ſight and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle, filled for a ſeaſon with conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ernation; but now they are got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to their old wont again, and recovered their frights and am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, dried up their tears, and wiped their eyes, and they are where they were before: this ſhews that this Judgement had no depth of efficacy upon your ſouls, it was onely ſomething external; it ſhews what your nature is. Oh, that's of a cold nature indeed, that will freeze while the fire is under it. Let all ſuch conſider, that they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn God, and harden their own hearts, and if he do not wonderfully ſet in it will be to their own deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> III. For <hi>Exhortation</hi> and <hi>Direction.</hi> Oh let it be an awaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing word of Counſel to us all. We are now come together to affect our ſouls with this ſtupend Judgement of God which is among us, the Lord in mercy grant that it may teach us Righteouſneſs; the voice of God cries aloud by it to this poor Town in a ſpecial manner, the Lord give us an hearing ear: let it be our great requeſt, that he would <hi>bore our ear to inſtruction,</hi> that it may not paſs by without doing us true and ſaving good. For <hi>Motive:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Let us conſider the awfulneſs of the Judgement it ſelf: this is none of thoſe ordinary diſpenſations of Gods Providence which are frequent and uſual in the world, to be ſure not among us; it is no common ſickneſs and calamity, and yet if it had been no more it had been our duty to have wiſely conſidered it, and given attention to the voice of it; but it is extraordinary and ſtupendious: it is not uſuall for God to give Satan ſuch liberty and power, ſo to rack and torture, ſo to hurry and perplex poor creatures, and therefore ſomething is in ſpecial to be learned by us, when God thus leaves the common track, and comes in ſo unwonted a way of Judgement.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider how nearly we are related unto it above other in the Land: there is a voice in it to the whole Land, but in a more eſpecial manner to poor <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> it is not a Judgement afar off, but it is near us, yea among us, God hath in his wiſdome ſingled out this poor Town out of all others in this Wilderneſs, to diſpenſe ſuch an ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Providence in, and therefore let us make a more near and ſpecial
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:107003:20"/> uſe of it: Let us look upon our ſelves to be ſet up as a <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> upon a Hill</hi> by this Providence, and let thoſe that hear what hath been done among us, hear alſo of the good effects, and reformation it hath wrought among us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider what advantage we have above others to be affected with it: others indeed may hear of it, relations may be carried from one place to another, and that may affect, yet not ſo much as when it is ſeen. Why, we may ſay as <hi>Job, I have heard of thee with the hearing of the ear, but now mine eye ſees thee.</hi> Reports may be carried various, and that may wound a great part of the credit of it abroad in the world, as not knowing how or where to faſten their belief; however, when never ſo truly reported, it cannot carry the life of the thing with it: but we have ſeen, yea ſeen ſuch things as one would think might melt, or break an heart of ſtone; we may carry about with us every day, the very pourtraicture of thoſe Helliſh and Diabolicall Cruelties, thoſe ſtrange Geſtures, thoſe dreadful Voices: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if we be not awed and affected by it, who ſhould?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Conſider how ſaid it will be for us, if we be not awed and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with this Judgement, if we learn nothing by it: Oh how much will God have againſt us, above others! the nearer he hath come to us, and the more we are concerned in it, and the louder the Cry hath been to us, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l all have their particular weight to increaſe our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, God will lay every circumſtance to our charge, and as he hath ſingularly revealed his minde to us in it, ſo he will have a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar provocation by it. Oh! little do we know how much this provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſlighted and miſimproved will adde to the weight of our ſins, and increaſe of our woes. Let it then be a ſolemn leſſon to teach us Righteouſneſs. For <hi>Direction:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Let us all in general learn ſomething by it, let it afford us ſome practical concluſions, which may be for our uſe and benefit to inſtruct and teach us in wayes of Righteouſneſs; namely,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Learn by it that Satan is buſie in places of Goſpel light, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce and draw away Souls from attending the means of grace. The Light of the Goſpel doth not clear and free places from Satan or his bold Temptations, theſe infernal Spirits of darkneſs will come thither, and there endeavour to raiſe miſts and fogs to ſeduce ſouls; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us learn not to live ſecurely under the enjoyment of the Goſpel of grace, but to <hi>ſpend our time of ſojourning her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in holy fear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:107003:21"/>2. That there is no place free, no not the Houſe of God from Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans Temptations: when thou art in Gods Houſe, and thy bodily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence to attend the Ordinances, the diſpenſing of the Goſpel, Satan will come thither, as he often did to this poor creature, he will do all he can to ſteal away thy minde and meditation, he will begin a parly with thee that ſhall laſt as long as the Sermon, and thou ſhalt go away without receiving one word of inſtruction. Oh how can he pleaſe thy fancy, and delude thy ſoul! and therefore let it awaken thee to be careful to <hi>keep thy foot when thou comeſt to the houſe of God,</hi> if thou <hi>wouldeſt not offer the ſacrifice of fools,</hi> Eccleſ. 5. 1. The feet of the ſoul are the Affections, learn to be more watchful over them, to keep them from wandring, leſt Satan meet and make a prey of them, and ſo ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al away the ſeed of the Word from thee.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That diſcontent layes us exceeding open to the aſſaults of Satan, and gives him more then ordinary advantage to make diſcoveries of himſelf to us: little do we know how we do as it were invite the Devil by it. In any Government, diſcontented perſons are fitteſt for Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to work upon: by diſcontent we diſcover a wearineſs of Gods Government, and therefore Satan is emboldened by it to come, yea to make his Apparitions, and ſtrike in to the drawing over of poor crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to enter a <hi>Covenant of Rebellion</hi> with him, and a wonder it is if any at ſuch a time eſcape. Learn we therefore to be more watchfull over our own hearts, beware how we give any way to ſecret up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſings againſt the Providence of God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That this world would be a ſad place to live in, if it were not for Gods over-ruling Providence. Oh how buſie is the Devil, that great Adverſary of Souls! and how full is he of Cruelty! did not God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain his rage, he would ſoon make poor Mortals incapable of living here below: By the Claw you may judge of the Lion. We finde in <hi>Jobs</hi> caſe, he goes to the outſide of his Commiſſion: and here you have a lively ſpectacle of his venome and ſpight; Oh then let it awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken us to ſee by whom we are every day preſerved and protected from the rage of Devils, God onely: Alas! what were we in the hands of theſe infernal Powers, if Gods Omnipotency did not reſtrain them. Let this make God more glorious in our eyes.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That there is no ſafety but under the wings of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: he onely is the <hi>ſtrong man</hi> that can ſecure us from the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Satan. Satan rules and reigns in this world, and you ſee how
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:107003:21"/> much power he holds over the children of diſobedience. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore learn hence both to bleſs God for Chriſt Jeſus, who came into the world to <hi>deſtroy the works of the Devil;</hi> had he not come to ſet up his Kingdome in this world, the Devil would have reigned Lord and King in all Souls, he onely is able to diſpoſſeſs the ſtrength, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle the Powers of Hell: as alſo to fly under the wings of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer for ſafeguard, that we may be freed from theſe cruel Enemies.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That viſible Priviledges are no ſecurity from Satan: it's not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to be <hi>baptized with water,</hi> un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s we be alſo <hi>baptized with the holy Ghoſt, and with fire;</hi> it's not enough to be a Member of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church, if we be not alſo of Chriſts inviſible Flock: Satan is not te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ified by theſe outward things, he is not afraid to aſſault thoſe that are Chriſts nominally, and to endeavour to make them his own really. Let it teach us then to beware that we <hi>truſt not in lying words,</hi> have a care of crying <hi>The Temple of the Lord;</hi> Satan deſires no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter advantage upon us, then to draw us to reſt ſecure upon this bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom. Bleſs God for our Priviledges, but reſt not in them; prize, but do not deifie them, if you would not be made the prey of Satan.</p>
            <p>2ly, Let us all in particular <hi>learn righteouſneſs</hi> by this monument that is before us, let it awaken us all to reform our hearts and lives, to be more careful to and over our ſelves for the time to come; let it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed appear that we have been proficients in this School of Gods Judgements, that God hath brought <hi>Correction</hi> and <hi>Teaching</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that ſo in the winding up it may be found an happy Judgement. Let us therefore apply it to our ſelves in our particular reſpects.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Let it be a Doctrinal Providence to <hi>Young</hi> and <hi>Old.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, To you that are <hi>Elder,</hi> and more grown up in years, let it awaken you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider how many more provocations God hath had from you, then he hath had from this poor creature; how many more Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances and Providences have attended upon you, then ever did upon her; think how long you have lived in Gods world, and yet have done him little or no ſervice ſince you came into it: and therefore let this awaken you to ſee how it ſtands with you, how the matter goes between God and your Souls, whether you are ſecure under his wings, and at peace with him. When you ſee one ſo much younger then you thus viſited, Oh think upon what ground you ſtand, fear
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:107003:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> the like or worſe, if you are yet in an uncertain ſtate. Let it in a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial manner awaken old ones to <hi>make their calling and election ſure,</hi> conſidering how much danger you are in.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let it teach you how much you have had of the patience of God exerciſed towards you, that God hath born with and forborn you ſo long; you have lived a great while longer in the world, and it may be have been more enormous and flagitious in your lives-then<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever this poor creature was: poſſibly you have lived in ſcandalous ſins, and grievous pollutions: if you ſhould conſider, and ask a Reaſon why God hath taken her and not taken you, you may ſee and ſay, that if God had gone according to outward appearance, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of rigour, there had been tranſcendently more ground why he ſhould have come upon you. Oh then, when you ſee one ſo young, and one not obſerved to be guilty of any flagitious crimes taken, while you are by Gods goodneſs ſpared, learn to admire at, and worſhip the patience of God towards you.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let it therefore teach you to amend your wayes, and reform your lives, and that ſpeedily: it may be a great argument to quicken you up no longer to uſe delayes, nor put off God coming to you in his Word, and perſwading you by his Spirit to repent and return to him. Oh ſee in this lecture upon what ſlippery and dangerous ground you ſtand, and have ſtood all this while, and if God had been ſevere towards you, you had not had this opportunity of being called to Repentance; and then learn to ſhake off all delayes, to put by all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes, and bleſs God that you yet have an opportunity.</p>
            <p>Secondly, You that are <hi>Young ones,</hi> behold here one of your Tribe and Form, as I may ſay, one of your own years pickt out of you by the wiſe Providence of God, to be made an object of Gods ſeverity, and mans pity. Out of doubt there is an eſpecial Cry to you <hi>Young ones,</hi> to <hi>Remember your Creator in the dayes of your youth:</hi> you have been often counſelled and admoniſhed in the Houſe of God, yea ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly and compaſſionately intreated to devote your young time to God, to give up the prime of your years to him; but you have ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and diſregarded ſuch Counſels and Calls, and have taken up firm reſolutions that you would have your childiſh and youthful vanities, let God by his Meſſenger ſay what he would to you: Well, now God hath ſingled you out in his Providence, and thunders out his minde to you in this ſad Object, and what do you now ſay to it? will you hear
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:107003:22"/> Gods voice, or will you forbear? are you ſtill reſolved in your vain courſes, or will you <hi>learn Righteouſneſs?</hi> if you would but encline your ears, you might here obſerve God ſpeaking ſomething to you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Learn, that there is no ſafety in dallying with the Spirit of God; who comes early to beſpeak your Souls for God. God ſhews that he hath a quarrel with the Youth for ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ghting and deſpiſing Counſels and Reproofs; he would that you ſhould know he is in haſte for an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and will not wait long if you trifl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> away your time: God looks that where there is ſo much of <hi>Goſpel light<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and ſo many endeavours uſed by Church and Common-wealth for the inſtruction of Youth in the Wayes of God, there ſhould be anſwerable improvement made, and will have you to know that his patience will not wait ſo long as in places of ignorance. Let it therefore teach you to beware how you preſume upon <hi>hereafter,</hi> and promiſing your ſelves that there is time enough, you may follow your vain courſes yet a little longer: W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>les you are thinking it is too ſoon to repent and amend, how ſoon may God come and declare that it is too late, that his patience is ſpent, and there is no more room left for Repentance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That either God or the Devil will have your young time: you are here at your choice, God by his Word and Spirit is tendring you to receive you into his ſervice, and declaring how acceptable and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it will be to him, but if you will not give your time to him, you will to a worſe Maſter, the Devil ſtands waiting, yea endeavouring for you, and if Gods yoke pleaſe you not, he will eaſily perſwade you to take his; and though that may ſeem delightful for the preſent, yet know it, <hi>it will be bitterneſs in the latter end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That if <hi>Young ones</hi> will not have Chriſt to reign over them, he may give them over into the hands and power of Satan: if Chriſts ſweet government do not pleaſe you, you ſhall be left under the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and cruelty of the Devil. Oh then learn hence not to deſpiſe and contemn the Calls of the Goſpel, leſt God come out in Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt you, and put you into the everlaſting poſſeſſion of that cruel Enemy of your Souls.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Let this Providence teach both <hi>Parents</hi> and <hi>Children:</hi> Here is ſomething for both.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Let it be a teaching Providence to you that are <hi>Parents,</hi> do you <hi>learn</hi> Leſſons of <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> by it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let it affect you with the dangerous caſe and ſtate of your poor
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:107003:23"/> Childrens Souls: here you may ſee how open they are by nature to Satans temptations, how they every day go in danger of thoſe ſly and ſubtile aſſaults of this politick enemy of their Souls: let this lye near your hearts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hence let this teach you to be careful in Educating them in the <hi>nurture and admonition of the Lord,</hi> which is the onely way and means to prevent this adverſary. If you have hitherto been remiſs, learn now to be more careful and vigilant about it, let it be a quickning pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence to rouſe you up from this neglect, by teaching you the great weight of the duty, even of as much moment as the precious lives of their poor ſouls.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let it teach you to begin with them betimes, do not defer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing of them too long; you ſee Satan will ſet upon them early, he will not delay long before he comes and uſeth his endeavours to draw your Childrens ſouls away after him: and therefore if you would prevent him, do not you delay, but be dropping in inſtruction as they are able, and as ſoon as they are able to underſtand any thing.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whitherſoever they go, bear a holy jealouſie over them, leſt they ſhould offend God, and provoke him to leave them to the Devil: you cannot be alwayes with them, nor conſtantly have them under your eye, but where-ever they be, be ſure let your hearts go along with them, have a righteous fear concerning them: you ſee Satan is ready to take all occaſions to inſinuate himſelf into them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for ought you know they may have the Devil in their company. let that direct your ſouls to heaven for them, that God would look to them, and preſerve them: <hi>Job</hi> offers Sacrifice for his Children, when met in lawful recreation, <hi>leſt they had ſinned, and curſed God in their hearts,</hi> Job 1. 5.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Be more watchful over them hereafter, then you have been heretofore; have a care of letting them have their ſwing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, to go and come where and when they pleaſe, and eſpecially in the night; be ſure take an account of their buſineſs, and hold your Parental Authority over them, keep them within their bounds, you had better bear their hard thoughts of you now, then ſee them made vaſſals of Satan, and left up to Gods Judgements. If your Children reſiſt or contemn your Authority, the Will of God is that you ſhould not bear with them, nor ſpare them; it is a great deal better they ſhould live in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:107003:23"/> 
               <hi>Bridewell</hi> under reſtraint, then in your Families at their liberty.</p>
            <p n="6">6. See to your own lives, that they be exemplary to your Children, if you teach them never ſo carefully, yet if you unteach them again by your vain converſation before them, its little the better: think how much advantage you put into Satans hands againſt your Children, to draw them into ſin by your example, he knows well enough what a taking argument this is with Children.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Reſt not ſatisfied, but be conſtant and earneſt with God for your Children till you ſee <hi>Chriſt formed in them,</hi> as knowing that till then they are in Satans Kingdome, and under his Juriſdiction. Oh what bowels of affection, what earneſt requeſts might this providence arm us withall! how ſtrong might it make us with God for our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren! O pity them in a ſtate of unregeneracy Chriſtleſs ſouls are naked ſouls, and therefore lye open to the enemy; ceaſe not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore night nor day begging for them. See in this providence their danger, and let it quicken you to importunacy.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Children</hi> do you learn ſomething hence alſo.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Learn to hearken to the loving and wholeſom Counſels of your Parents, and not to ſlight or deſpiſe their Admonitions and Reproofs. You ſee here how open you are to Satans aſſaults, and if you will not hear God ſpeaking to you by your Parents, it is juſt with God to leave you to the Devil, to hear him: know it, when your Parents ſpeak to you, and adviſe you for your good, God ſpeaks to you by them, and if <hi>your eye deſpiſe them,</hi> God may ſuffer theſe infernal <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens</hi> and <hi>Eagles to pick it out, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at it.</hi> One would think this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument might make you fear and tremble.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Learn hence not to truſt to your Parents Covenant, or to think that you ſhall be ſaved by their Faith, or by it ſecured from Satan: it is true, you may fare the better by them and for them, but if you reſt upon their godlineſs for your ſecurity, you are deceived: you may be the natural Children of godly Parents, and yet the ſpiritual Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Devil, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8. 43, 44. Know it, it is not enough to be the Children of godly Parents, unleſs you do inherit their graces: ſeek therefore that, or elſe Satan hath you at his beck.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Reſt not upon your Parents Prayers; think it not enough that your godly Parents pray for you to God, and therefore you are ſafe: true, Parents Prayers are a great benefit to Children, but if they be truſted to, they will prove a meer deluſion. <hi>Abraham</hi> prayes for
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:107003:24"/> 
               <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> but he prayes not for himſelf: God may anſwer your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents Prayers in another way, they ſhall not loſe them, but yet if you reſt there, they may but increaſe your woes. Let this therefore call upon you to make your own peace.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Learn to obey your Parents in all their lawful Commands, and that in obedience unto God: acknowledge their authority and juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction over you, and though they reſtrain you from that which you may think to be a lawful liberty, yet be obedient in all things lawful, for though the thing be a matter indifferent, yet if you diſobey and diſpleaſe your Parents in it, be ſure you lay your ſelves open to Satan.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Let it teach both the <hi>Regenerate,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nregenerate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, You that are <hi>Regenerated,</hi> and brought home to God, you may learn ſomething here.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let this providence teach you to magnifie Gods grace, that hath taken you out of Satans Kingdome, and <hi>tranſlated you into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of his own Son.</hi> When-ever we ſee any left by God, and in any wayes in the hand of Satan, and under his power, how ſhould it fill us with God-glorifying thoughts, at the conſideration of his wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full love to us. Now is a time to conſider who made the difference between two pieces of the ſame clay, to remember how oppoſite we were to any ſaving good, what pains God took with us, what per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions he uſed, and how contumeliouſly we often handled his Spirit; to conſider that if his love had not carried him againſt our hatred, had not he pitied us, when we did not, could not pity our ſelves, we had yet to this day been under the dominion of Hell.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let it awaken you to <hi>walk worthy of your vocation; you now ſee your calling,</hi> you are called one of Satans kingdome, you are delivered from the powers of darkneſs, labour then to walk no longer <hi>in the vanity of your mindes:</hi> Are you Gods Children? <hi>Live in holineſs, 1 Pet. 1. 14, &amp;c.</hi> Oh that this Providence might awaken thoſe that have given up themſelves to God and his Service, to conſider whether we have not too much gratified Satan, by being too light, too vain, too exceſſive in taking liberty in worldly mirth and vanity, too little ſpiritual in our courſe and converſation among men. Let it then be a word of Warning to us to be more ſerious and cautious to our ſelves and wayes for the time to come.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let it move in you earning bowels of compaſſion towards thoſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:107003:24"/> that are yet in Satans Kingdome, and under his ſpiritual Juriſdiction: you may here ſee a little, though but a little, yet ſo much appears here viſible and demonſtrative, as may give a glimpſe of diſcovery how ſad and doleful the condition of poor unregenerate ſinners is, who are <hi>ſpiritually poſſeſt by Satan.</hi> Let it then rouſe up in you bowels of pity, when you look in the faces of any ſuch, let it make you to mourn over them, and pray for them, and counſel and adviſe them as God gives you opportunity, that if it may be, you may be helpful to their eſcape out of the paws of the devouring Lion.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Let it awaken you to watch your wayes and actions, to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to your lives and courſes, how you carry it before them who are yet in their vanity, leſt Satan make you his <hi>Stales</hi> to allure poor ſouls by. If the Devil can <hi>belye</hi> the people of God to encourage others to hearken to him, be ſure he will make his market of <hi>your failings,</hi> negligent walkings, and whatſoever is done amiſs by you at one time or other, to draw others more ſearieſly after him; and will it not be a ſad thing that ſouls ſhould follow Satan to their eternal ruine and perdition, and you the live-birds that have drawn them into this net? For the Lords ſake, for the love you bear to poor ſouls, if there be any pity, any compaſſion, any deſire to Gods glory, or others Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, look to your wayes, and ſee they be exemplary.</p>
            <p>Secondly, You that are <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nregenerate,</hi> labour to hear the voice of God in this Providence, and learn by it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let this Example teach you how <hi>cruel a Maſter</hi> you ſerve: you ſee here, that Satan (whatever pretences he makes, and fair promiſes he ſeeks to delude poor ſouls withall) is in his heart ſet againſt all mankinde, and he ſeeks only to deſtroy them; and if once God lets him looſe, and gives him liberty, he will ſoon ſhew his own nature, and give evidence of his Cruelty. This you have ſeen is but a little of that bitter ſpight he will exerciſe upon thoſe who ſhall be wholly deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered into his hands. You have little cauſe to boaſt of your condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, its a cruel bondage, you are in the hands of one whoſe <hi>tender mercies are cruelty.</hi> Oh that this might make you weary of Satans go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, that it might make you begin to diſcover his policies, and flee from him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let it ſhew you the great danger you go in every hour of being made a prey to Satan. Conſider how ready this Adverſary is to faſten his T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lons upon poor creatures, if God permit him: and conſider
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:107003:25"/> that thou haſt no ſecurity, no ground to promiſe thy ſelf that God will defend thee from him, no not for a moment, it is Gods goodneſs that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he hath hitherto afforded thee his protection, but thou haſt no promiſe that he will continue it: Yea conſider, how many Calls and Counſels, how many Providences and Ordinances thou haſt deſpiſed, how often God hath come to thee, and wooed earneſtly for thy ſoul, uſed heart-breaking intreaties with thee, endeavouring to inſinuate himſelf into thy very ſoul, and yet thou haſt hardned thy heart againſt all, and reſolutely refuſed: think then, what haſt thou to ſay for thy ſelf why thou mayeſt not ſpeedily hear God ſay to the Devil, <hi>Take the full and everlaſting poſſeſſion of ſuch a ſoul?</hi> and what will become of thee then?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Hence let it be a loud Cry to you to Repentance: You have had many Cries in your ears from the Word, but you have not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved the report which Gods Meſſengers have brought. Oh that you would believe when God addes ſuch a Confirmation to the truth of his Word! reade your own ſtate in this poor Monument, and think by what you ſee in her, what is like to become of you in the ſtate you are in; hearken, and you may heat God crying to you by her, <hi>Except ye repent, ye ſhall all likewiſe periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, let me return once again to all that are here in Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence this day to humble themſelves before him: learn we hence, for this day, and hence-forward, theſe two Leſſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let us all examine by this Providence what ſins they have been, that have given Satan ſo much footing in this poor place: ſure the voice of God is loud to us, and bids us to bring this matter upon ſearch; for though God be Soveraign. yet it is to us a time of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration when Gods hand is out againſt us, <hi>Hag.</hi> 1. 7. Let it then bring us upon a ſerious Triall of our ſelves and wayes, that we may be able to trace God in his Providence, and acknowledge his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judgements; let us ask whether our <hi>Contentions</hi> have not ſet open this door, and invited Satan in? I am ſure theſe carry a very great reſemblance of the Devils <hi>Cloven Foot.</hi> Have not our <hi>Heart-Diviſions</hi> grieved away the Spirit of God, and given Satan this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage? I am ſure they leave a people faulty, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 10 2. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore lay them open to ſevere puniſhments: theſe have been too gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſins, and what have been in particular? What a deal of <hi>Worldly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindedneſs</hi> in the elder ſort? the <hi>vanity</hi> and <hi>looſeneſs</hi> in the younger,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:107003:25"/> increaſed to ſuch a height of impudency. Let me adde, the general <hi>light eſteem</hi> there hath been among us of Gods holy and precious <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances,</hi> and <hi>contempt</hi> of his <hi>Meſſengers:</hi> theſe are crying ſins, and therefore may well be anſwered with loud-ſpeaking Providences.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us all joyn heart and hand to drive this Enemy out again. Let that be our great buſineſs this day to implore God, and beg his aſſiſtance and direction in ſo great a Work as this is; and let us forthwith ſet upon it, and follow it might and main: and that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance of, and humiliation for what is paſt, and reformation for the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ture, <hi>let us ſearch and try our wayes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and turn again to the Lord;</hi> Let us lay aſide <hi>Envy</hi> and <hi>Malice,</hi> throw down our <hi>Contention</hi> &amp; <hi>Strife,</hi> and take up <hi>Peace and Love.</hi> Let the Aged reform their <hi>Earthly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindedneſs,</hi> and the Youth their <hi>Vanity,</hi> their Night-walkings, and me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry Drinking-meetings; let the <hi>Judgements of God</hi> awe our hearts, and leave ſuch impreſſions behinde them, as may powerfully lead us in wayes of Righteouſneſs, that God may delight to dwell among us, and <hi>tread Satan under our feet.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:107003:26"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ISAIAH 21. 11, 12.</bibl>
               <q>11 The burden of Dumah. He calleth to me out of S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir, Watchman, what of the night? watchman, what of the night?</q>
               <q>12 The watchman ſaid, The morning cometh, and alſo the night: if ye will enquire, enquire ye: return, come.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>TImes of publick Calamity, either felt, or juſtly feared, are try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Times; theſe do call in a ſolemn manner for Conſideration, and eſpecially to enquire into the Cauſes, and bethink of the ſad E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents. This is <hi>New<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Englands</hi> day, wherein God hath at leaſt taken the Rod into his hand, and is ſhewing ſome part of his ſeverity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward us; and though he mix it with much moderation, yet there is a great deal of bitterneſs in the Cup: 'tis time therefore humbly to enquire into the grounds, and conſider of the Conſequences of theſe Calamities. The Text before us may afford us ſomething by way of Inſtruction and Direction in this enquiry.</p>
            <p>The words are a Propheſie againſt <hi>Dumah,</hi> delivered by way of <hi>Queſtion</hi> and <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Queſtion</hi> is propounded <hi>ver.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Anſwer</hi> is ſhort, full, and ſharp, <hi>ver.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>The meaning of the words take up as they come to be handled in particular.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The burden] i. e.</hi> A Propheſie containing Threatnings of Wrath, and Predictions of Miſery: an ordinary phraſe it is among the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, to expreſs any Viſion of ſad conſequence. See <hi>Chap.</hi> 13. 1. and this Chapter, <hi>ver.</hi> 1, 13. and therefore the Prophet interprets the ſenſe of the word, <hi>ver. 2. An hard Viſion.</hi> See alſo 2 <hi>Kings 9 25. Jer.</hi> 23. 33. and elſwhere. Hence</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>The denunciations of Gods wrath againſt a ſinning people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s a Burden, a thing heavy and grievous.</hi> In divers conſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are <hi>a burden to Gods Meſſengers;</hi> i. e. grievous and hard to them, their ſpirits are oppreſſed, and many times even overwhelmed within them, to fore-think of the meſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge they have to deliver.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:107003:26"/>
            <p>Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ver. 3, 4. Chap 15. 5. &amp; 16. 9. Jer. 48. 31, 32. &amp;</hi> 4. 19, 20.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are a <hi>burden to the People</hi> to whom they are ſent. This in two reſpects:</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) They are <hi>a burden of grief and ſorrow</hi> to the godly, who hear and fear, <hi>Hab.</hi> 3. 16.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Of <hi>indignation</hi> to the wicked, who cannot endure ſo much as to hear of them, the very Threatning is to them intolerable, <hi>Amos 7. 10. 2 Chron. 36. 16. Jer.</hi> 26. 8, 9.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In ſome ſenſe they are <hi>a burden to God,</hi> who ſpeaking after the manner of men, expreſſeth a rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ing at the very mention of it, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11. 8. 9.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>A burden in the Effects</hi> of them, or matter of Threatning con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in them, which is fore and heavy to bear: Context, <hi>ver.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Reaſons</hi> are:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of the firſt; From the ſympathetical comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſionateneſs of Gods Meſſengers towards their fellow-creatures, there is a <hi>Philan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thropy,</hi> A love of man naturally in man, this is increaſed by grace: this we ſee eminent in <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 9. 1. and <hi>Moſes, Blot me rather out of thy book.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Of the ſecond; From the ſenſe of the ſeverity of Gods diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure in the godly, and hence it produceth ſorrow for their ſins.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) It brings ſin to minde, which is the Cauſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25. 17, 18.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) The people of God know what a ſad thing it is to have to do with an angry God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76. 7.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Of the third; From the pride of heart which is in the wicked, <hi>Jer.</hi> 43. 2. they are too good to be reproved, will not hear by reaſon of the height of their ſpirits, think ſo well of themſelves, that they cannot believe that God is diſpleaſed at them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Of the fourth; From the compaſſions of God towards poor ſinners, he herein diſcovers his merciful Nature, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11. 8.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Of the fifth; From the averſneſs of the nature of man from ſorrows and miſeries: they are againſt our nature, and therefore muſt needs be burdenſome; yea they are Puniſhments, and are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore grievo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> I. See here a Reaſon why Gods Warnings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Threatnings finde no more welcome, and why plain Preaching Miniſter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are hated: ſinning man is gotten above warning, though by our ſins we are pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g down Gods Judgements upon ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> heads, all this is nothing, but
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:107003:27"/> he that tells us plainly of them, and repreſents the anger of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us for them, he is <hi>the troubler of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> II. Learn hence to interpret the Threatnings of Judgement denounced by Gods Meſſengers in the beſt ſenſe, when they tell you of Gods wrath. Oh do not think they tell you as they would have it, or that they take any delight in bringing ſuch heavy tidings, but they muſt ſay as God commands them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 28. 6. they can be gladly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that the threatning may never be fulfilled.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> III. Here is a mark to diſtinguiſh the people of God from hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritical Profeſſors: when God tells us plainly of our ſins, and ſpeaks of his wrath, 'tis indeed <hi>a burden</hi> to all; but how? why, the wicked endeavour to throw it off themſelves, and caſt it upon Gods Miniſters, and violently to pull their ſhoulder from under it; but the people of God ſit down under it, and bear it patiently, yea take up a new <hi>burden of ſorrow</hi> for the ſin which hath procured it, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. 27, 28, 39.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> IV. Learn hence what uſe to make of the threatning of Gods Judgements, and Reproofs of your ſins, if it be <hi>a burden</hi> to hear of them, what then will it be to bear them? if you cannot endure to ſit quietly whiles you are told of them, how will you endure when God ſhall do according to the word of his Meſſengers? Let ſuch thoughts as theſe move you to prepare your ſelves, this uſe God would have theſe burdens attain, <hi>Amos</hi> 4. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of Dumah] i. e.</hi> Of the Land of <hi>Idumea,</hi> the place of the poſterity of <hi>Eſau,</hi> called <hi>Ed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m:</hi> theſe were, though of the poſterity of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> yet a Nation rejected by God, and become an Heathen Nation; and yet God tells them aforehand what he intends againſt them, and condeſcends to give them a Warning to Repentance. Hence</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>God, though grievouſly provoked, yet ſeldome brings deſolating Judgements, before he gives warning. Edom,</hi> though out of Gods Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, ſhall never theleſs hear from God before they feel his wrath, and <hi>Babylon,</hi> and <hi>Arabia,</hi> and <hi>Tyre,</hi> &amp;c. as we finde ſcattered in the Propheſies, how much more a people in Covenant with him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. Becauſe this is the day of Gods forbearance, and therefore he will exalt it towards ſinners, and make them to taſte of it. It is the time wherein Juſtice is moderated by Mercy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That ſinners may have an opportunity to repent: when God ſpeaks to them before he ſtrikes them, he puts <hi>a price into their hands,</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:107003:27"/> if they have but <hi>a heart to it;</hi> hence God calls them to it. Text looks on it as ſuch a ſeaſon, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 21.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To take off all excuſe in the day of Vengeance, that all mouthes may be ſtopt, ſinners ſhall have nothing to ſay for themſelves, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been warned<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they ſhall have no plea, ſhall not b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> able to ſay, <hi>We never heard of it:</hi> no cloak ſhall be left them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> This may be a Rule to teach us what uſe to make of thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold Warnings which God vouchſafes to afford unto us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hearken to his <hi>Warnings,</hi> hear his Threatnings, attend to them, and believe them.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>How doth God warn us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, By his <hi>Meſſengers,</hi> theſe are Ambaſſadors, to declare the minde and counſel of God, and proclaim his Judgements.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But Revelations ceaſe, how then can they give us a true account of the minde of God, and his purpoſes of bringing Judgements on us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> God gives a greater portion of his Spirit to his Miniſters, then to others, and by that Spirit he extraordinarily</p>
            <p n="1">1. Stirs them up to a conſideration of his minde and counſels: he directs their thoughts that way.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Diſcovers to them the ſins of the times and places they live in, makes them to obſerve the frames and manners of the people he ſends them to.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Enables them to compare his ancient dealings with ſinners, in the ſeveral reſpects and circumſtances, and hence to draw concluſions, and hence verifies that promiſe, <hi>Amos</hi> 3. 7. Now theſe Concluſions are <hi>a ſure word of Propheſie:</hi> for</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Rule is ſtanding, <hi>Crying ſins are anſwered with certain Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> God is the ſame he was, his Holineſs and Juſtice remain in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable, and unchangeable, and therefore ſinners have no hopes to eſcape, if they remain in their ſins.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Like ſins bring like Judgements; <hi>Sodoms</hi> ſins are followed with <hi>Sodems</hi> plagues; and therefore if our ſins anſwer former times, we may expect our ſufferings to be like theirs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Propheſies of the Prophets were cautioned with the condition of Repentance, either explicite, as appears by the invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to repent annexed to their Threatnings frequently; or at leaſt implicite, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18. 7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo are theirs.</p>
            <p>Secondly, By his <hi>Providences:</hi> gathering of Clouds, and ſome
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:107003:28"/> drops of rain preſage a Sto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, Signs ſpeak, the Rod hath a voice in i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and may be heard, though it be but ſhaken over us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let the <hi>Patience</hi> of God break our hearts, and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ead us to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> Rom. 2. 4. Remember, God might have ſtricken when he warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us; he might have made <hi>our plagues ſeven times heavier,</hi> when he did lay ſome gentler ſtroke upon us; he might have made haſte, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, and made an end with us in one day, after he had ſo long in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience waited upon us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Give credit to <hi>Gods Threatnings,</hi> do not think he is in jeſt, look at ſuch times wherein Ordinances and Providences concur in denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing wrath againſt us, to be reall tokens of Divine Diſpleaſure, and to have a loud voice in them; and therefore let it teach us to meet God, and that without delay.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He calleth,</hi> &amp;c.] Here is the <hi>queſtion</hi> or <hi>Introduction</hi> to the Propheſie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He</hi>] i. e. Some Perſon, or Meſſenger.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Calleth</hi>] i. e. Comes to enquire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To me</hi>] i. e. <hi>Iſaiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Out of Seir</hi>] Mount <hi>Seir</hi> lying in the Land of the <hi>Edomites,</hi> is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for the whole Land of <hi>Idumea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Watchman, what,</hi> &amp;c.] By Watchman is meant the <hi>Prophet,</hi> theſe are called <hi>Watchmen</hi> by God, becauſe he ſets them to diſcern his wrath, and give warning to the people. The meaning or intent of the <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion</hi> is diverſly underſtood: I finde a twofold interpretation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some take it to be an expreſſion of the bitterneſs and anguiſh of the <hi>Edomites,</hi> concerning the future event of thoſe troubles which were beginning upon them: it ſeems War was threatned by the <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyrian;</hi> through which anguiſh they ſend to the Prophet, to know what was likely to enſue, what troubles they ſhould meet withall: for <hi>Night</hi> is here a Metaphor of the time of affliction, as it is often in Scripture, <hi>Iſa. 26. 9, &amp;c.</hi> and then the ingemination of the Interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, implies an earneſtneſs of deſire to be informed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Others underſtand it to be ſpoken in a flouring way, and ſo they call the Prophet <hi>Watchman</hi> by way of deriſion; as if they ſhould ſay, <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> you pretend to be a Watchman, and have foretold much of the time of trouble and deſolation to come upon us, but we ſtill enjoy the morning of proſperity, we are a free people, and not in ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; come, what do you ſay to it now? Either interpretation will ſtand with the Analogie of Faith: though I think the latter to be
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:107003:28"/> more ſuitable to the <hi>Anſwer</hi> given in the following verſe; in which ſenſe the doubling of the <hi>Queſtion</hi> is an aggravation of the ſcoff in a ſarcaſmous ſpeech.</p>
            <p>From theſe words obſerve,</p>
            <p>Doct. 1. <hi>Times of Calamity are fitly compared to the night ſeaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is much of Analogie in theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the <hi>night</hi> nothing can be diſtinguiſhed from the darkneſs, all things lye equally mantled under that black veil; hence the Grave it called <hi>A land of darkneſs,</hi> becauſe all meet equally, and indiſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably there: in times of Calamity the affliction is univerſal, good and bad are not to be diſtinguiſhed by the outward face of Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cleſ</hi> 9. 1.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>night</hi> is a <hi>joyleſs time,</hi> darkneſs and obſcurity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ide from us object of joy and mirth: in times of Calamity objects of joy are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, theſe outward ſymptomes and expreſſions of delights and pleaſures are removed, <hi>Jer.</hi> 7. 34.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>night</hi> is <hi>full of terrour,</hi> the darkneſs hath a kinde of influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon our fantaſie, leaving an impreſſion of ſtrange apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſing us with fears. Calamitous times are fearful and terrible times, fill us with ſuſpitions, a man knows not whom to truſt, lives in a fearful expectation of ſudden miſeries to ſeize upon him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>night</hi> is a <hi>ſolitary time,</hi> breaks up ſocieties, and ſcattereth them to their ſeverall Chambers, to feed upon their melancholick thoughts and fears. Troubleſome times bring places full of inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants to ſit ſolitary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> I. See here a Reaſon why the people of God ought to do their utmoſt to prevent the day of Calamity: though they ſhall get good by all Providences, yet <hi>no affliction is</hi> in it ſelf <hi>joyous, but grievous,</hi> and they ſhall finde a great deal of <hi>night,</hi> of trouble at ſuch a time. Hence wonder not to hear them ſo earneſt to deprecate that day, and labour ſo with God for a prevention of it. Chriſt himſelf, in whom was no ſin, begs again and again, <hi>if it be poſſible that the Cup might paſs away</hi> from him, how much more they that have ſin as well as ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row to grapple withall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> II. See here the Analogie between <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Sorrow,</hi> both are in Scripture called <hi>darkneſs:</hi> hence the puniſhment is ſuitable to the fault, God payes men in their own Coin; if men will hurry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:107003:29"/> ſelves into the ſhades of ſin, God juſtly brings them into <hi>a land of darkneſs, and of the ſhadow of death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> III. This Conſideration may warn us to have a care how we provoke Gods Judgements againſt us, to bring wrath upon us; we may be bold and fearleſs while the day time laſts, and our Sun of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity ſhines upon us, but if we pull down Judgements upon our heads, we ſhall finde the <hi>night</hi> to be</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Joyleſs,</hi> we ſhall ſee the difference between joy and ſorrow ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentally: when God ſhall have removed our comforts away from us, our peace, our outward ſupplies, all our precious things, we ſhall then feel what it is to be benighted.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Terrible,</hi> full of amazement. Ah! little do we know what the terrour of this <hi>night</hi> mean, to be oppreſſed with pining hunger, with pinching penury; to hear the cries of Children following us for bread, and none to give them; to hear the ſound of the Trumpet, and Alarm to War; to hear the cries of the wounded, and ſee the ſlain in our gates; to ſee the raging of Famine and Peſtilence, and natural affection changed into a Tyger-like Cruelty, tender-hearted Mothers ſhutting up their bowels of pity, and laying violent hands on the Children they have born; to go into Captivity, and ſerve an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my whoſe tender mercies are cruelty; to live in fear of every ſight, every noiſe, leſt it ſhould be ſome meſſenger of Death, or that which is worſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Solitary</hi> and loneſome, when you ſhall be made deſolate, and like <hi>Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> who was made <hi>a ſtranger to the wife of his boſome;</hi> and hence you ſhall have that which will fill head and heart full of perplexity: how careful then ſhould we be that we provoke not God againſt us, to bring darkneſs of adverſity upon us.</p>
            <p>Doct. 2. <hi>'Tis the guiſe and diſpoſition of the wicked, to deſpiſe and ſcoff at the Thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tnings of Gods Judgement againſt them, eſpecially if God delay execution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the <hi>Edomites</hi> here, they had been threatned, but they yet were in peace, and though the Enemy was coming, they yet are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure. See alſo for this, <hi>Eccleſ. 8. 11. Ezek.</hi> 12. 22. Poor ſinning man, though he might reade the ſentence of death in himſelf, yet is not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to believe any evil till he feels it. If God delay, his Meſſengers preſently are L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1 From the natural ſecurity which poſſeſſeth the hearts of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:107003:29"/> the unregenerate: ſinful man is naturally ſecure, which ſecurity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth from</p>
            <p n="1">1. Their not ſeeing and being affected with their ſin, juſtly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking of God, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2. 7. men grope in their darkneſs, and cannot ſee wherein they have done amiſs. Men, eſpecially if they have taken <hi>a form of godlineſs,</hi> and begin to be ſticklers in Religion, they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve not that they want <hi>the power,</hi> and having taken up a good ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of themſelves, the Word of Conviction paſſeth by as a thing in which they are not concerned. Hence they wonder that God ſhould have any thing againſt them, they cannot believe it, and ſo they d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſpiſe, and make a mock of thoſe that tell them of Wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Their miſinterpretation of Gods patient dealing with them: Natural men make a God to themſelves of their own Mindes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 21. if God delayes them, then preſently he approves of their wayes; at leaſt they muſt have him a God all of mercy, they exa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t his Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſion to the injury and violation of his Holineſs and Juſtice; and ſo, what ſhould be a means of their Repentance, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 9. is an occaſion of their hardning.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Their falſe hopes and promiſes of their eſcape, their <hi>Covenant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with Hell and Death,</hi> Iſa. 28. 17, 18. make all men (thriving in the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld in a way of wickedneſs, and being rooted deep in their outward enjoyments) begin to account this a kinde of Deity to them, and hence build up their hopes and thoughts upon an unchangeable eſtate, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49. 11. and hence can diſdain, and flout away the denunciation of a change.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. Becauſe their preſent proſperity ſo takes up their ſenſes, that they deſpiſe God, no wonder then if they ſcoff at his Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſitting in the Pomp and Glory of the Crown of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> demands, <hi>Who is the Lord?</hi> Natural men are ready to ſay (in times of proſperity) with <hi>Niobe,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Major ſum quam cui poſſit fortuna nocer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am greater then the hand of Providence can reach to do any injury to, and hence beat a Challenge to the Almighty, <hi>Job</hi> 21. 13, 14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> I. See here a Reaſon why Gods Meſſengers are ſo ſlighted by a ſecure and proſpering people: when they ſpeak of dayes of wrath, men do not believe them, their Preaching is accounted as falſe tales &amp; vain ſtories; why, men live at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſe, and therefore they are accounted
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:107003:30"/> fools that ſpeak of a ſtorm, and are made a <hi>May-game</hi> of, as they do here of the Prophet: and no wonder, for they do ſo by God himſelf; <hi>I ſpake to thee in thy proſperity, and thou wouldeſt not hear.</hi> Men are ſhort ſighted, though they can diſcern the ſigns of Heaven, yet they are not willing to ſee any thing of the ſigns of Divine Diſpleaſure, and if they ſee nothing, they will believe nothing, yea though they do ſee they are not willing to believe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> II. To convince us of, and humble us for even this very ſin before God this day. God hath given <hi>New-England</hi> many dayes of proſperity, it hath been day with us a long time, but mean-while ſin hath been growing upon us, and increaſing, and Gods Meſſengers have dealt faithfully with us, and told us of it, and warned us by the clear demonſtrations of the Word of God, that Judgements hang over our heads, but have not theſe Admonitions been deſpiſed and mocked by us?</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>You will ſay, How?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. Some have mocked them in plain terms, we have not been clear of this brazen-faced impudence, ſome to flout at the Warnings of God, yea to hate thoſe that have been moſt ſerious in reproving our ſins, eſpecially that have pointed them out.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Others have not believed, and thoſe not a few neither, but the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſt: we may almoſt uſe the Prophets demand, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. 1.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Have not theſe Warnings been practically ſlighted and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regarded?</p>
            <p n="1">1. How few hearts have been affected? and not to be affected, is a degree of mocking: how few melting hearts? how few that hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and fear? how few tremblers at the Word of God? or that with old <hi>Eli, ſit by the way, trembling for the Ark of God?</hi> We can ſit under the Convictions of the Word, and no whit convinced; little remorſe when theſe <hi>burdens</hi> are laid upon us, and we go away and <hi>wipe our mouthes, and ſay, What have I done?</hi> We (like deaf men) ſtartle not when the Trumpet ſounds, becauſe we will not hear it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What little care is there to return and meet God by repentance, and what is this better then to ſlight and mock God?</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But many dayes of Humiliation have been kept?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> True; and to what purpoſe?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Where is the Reformation that hath followed? in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58. the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> owns that onely as a true Faſt, which is a day of Reformation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:107003:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> but what hath been amended? if we were amiſs before, we are ſo ſtill, notwithſtanding all that is made to appear to the view of the world: and this is a manifeſt mockery.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Have we not kept dayes to encourage our ſelves to ſin more boldly upon a new ſcore, with the Whore in <hi>Prov.</hi> 7. 14, 15? thought to have cleared all old ſcores with God by an overly Confeſſion, that ſo we might more ſecurely run into new arrerages: and is not this a great mockery, to think to pay God with ſuch counterfei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Coin? What have we to do then, but to confeſs and bewail this ſin be ore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God, and labour to amend it? For <hi>Motive:</hi> Conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. God will make you to know who ſent theſe Meſſengers; that it was not of their own heads, nor on their own errands, that his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters came to you, but that it was from him, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 25. and that you have not ſcoffed and neglected them, but God himſelf: you ſhall ſee this.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Gods patience hath a bounded time, <hi>Hab.</hi> 2. 3. God may delay long, he will not do ſo alwayes; know it, he is juſt as well as merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: God will take a ſeaſon, finde out a fit opportunity to be known in his Judgements upon thoſe who deſpiſe his patience, and reject his counſels and fore-warnings, he <hi>will not ſtrive alwayes with man, who is fleſh,</hi> Gen. 6. 3.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Such a ſpirit will provoke God to make haſte, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 12. 23. if God ſend, yea <hi>riſe up early and ſend,</hi> and ſo far condeſcend to a rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious people, as to ſend Meſſenger after Meſſenger, and Meſſage upon Meſſage, and theſe mocked and deſpiſed, that news quickly comes there is no remedy, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36. 16. this ripens men apace for deſtruction<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Such a ſpirit is an immediate fore-runner of ſwift Calamity, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 1—No ſurer and more infallible token of great Calamities to be haſtning upon a people then this, when God tells them of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and calamity, they cry <hi>Peace, Peace,</hi> and lay themſelves down (in deſpight of all Counſels and Warnings) upon the bed of Security, and take their eaſe in ſin without remorſe. Let us then be deeply af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with this evil, as knowing that there is nothing whereby we have more grievouſly provoked God, and vexed his Spirit, then by this: lye low before him in the ſenſe of it, it may be he will pardon and forgive it.</p>
            <p>Doct. 3. <hi>It is no ſure ſign of a ſincere heart, in times wherein Gods Judgements are felt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> about them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:107003:31"/>
            <p>You ſee <hi>Edom</hi> here makes a great do of Enquiry: there is an hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritical and falſe, and there is a ſincere and true Enquiry made about divine D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſpenſations, and the one apparently, and to the view of the world, may be as earneſtly preſſed as the other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. Becauſe there are other things which may excite ſuch an Enquiry, beſides the fear of God; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. A natural fear, which may be ſtirred up at the firſt hearing of Threatnings, and diſcovery of tokens preſaging Calamity; the ſight of diſmall Clouds, and the noiſe of ſome terrible Thunder-cracks, do at the firſt carry a kinde of conſternation along with them: and this makes men, till by degrees they outgrow their affrightment, to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſedulous to know what theſe things mean.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A naturally buſie talkative ſpirit, that loves to be buſie, talking and diſcourſing, many affect to be in diſcourſe, and hence they enquire that they may have ſomething to ſpend time in diſcourſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A deſire to be thought wiſe, diſcerning and prudent, hence men will enquire for light: we love to have the eſteem for prudence and diſcretion, to be accounted men of diſcerning ſpirits, that obſerve and know the times, and hence take ſome pains in ſearching.</p>
            <p n="4">4. An irohicall and flo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ting ſpirit: ſuch this ſeems to be in the Text, not that we have any true deſire to know any thing, but in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain of Gods Miniſters: we enquire of them as for knowledge, but in the mean-while look upon them to have no more knowledge of the minde and counſel of God then our ſelves: with this ſpirit thoſe <hi>proud men</hi> ſeem to have come to enquire of the Prophet, <hi>Jer.</hi> 43.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. Becauſe there are other ends of ſuch Enquiry, beſides ſuch as accompany ſincerity; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. A bare deſire of external knowledge and diſcourſe: there is ſeated in man a great natural deſire of the knowledge of the Nature of things, and that eſpecially of future Contingencies; hence men take a great deal of pains, and buſie themſelves much in ſeeking to know ſuch things, when it is to no other end but to know.</p>
            <p n="2">2. An intent to cavill at Gods diſpenſations, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58. 2. Some en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire to no other end, but that they may pick a quarrel with Divine Providence, and charge the wayes of God with injuſtice, as if they were wiſer then God, as if he did not Rule the World by an equall Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. For <hi>Tryall:</hi> there is much talk now a-dayes amongſt us,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:107003:31"/> about the Judgements of God, and thoſe awfull Providences that are rolling over our heads: there is a great Enquiry made, but let us not think or conclude our ſelves ever the better, becauſe we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the number of thoſe who are poſſibly the moſt forward upon this account, but examine our ſelves whether we do it in ſincerity or in hypocrifie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signs of hypocriticall Enquiry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. When we enquire more after the <hi>Events</hi> of Calamity, then the Cauſes procuring of it: thus thoſe <hi>Idumeans, What of the night?</hi> i. e. What is like to come upon us? So there is much enquiry, what the iſſue of theſe rolling Providences is like to be; what things are like to come to: but there are few ſay, What have I done? wherein is the Lords anger incenſed, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> this ſhews we are more afraid of ſorrow then ſin, when we look ſo much at the Rod, and not at the hand which wieldeth it: This argues a ſpirit of hypocriſie; for we neglect our work, which is to ſearch and try our hearts, and meddle with Gods work, whoſe Soveraignty it is to rule and order the affairs of the whole World at his own pleaſure.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When we enquire more after <hi>Natural</hi> then Spiritual <hi>Cauſes:</hi> we are very inquiſitive to know what may be the <hi>Natural Cauſe</hi> of theſe Blaſtings which have for many years diminiſhed and corrupted the beſt of our Grain; and hence, many projective endeavours in vain attempted to prevent it, by a ſeeking to remove that Cauſe, which we are to this day baffled in, and as far off to ſeek as ever: but the Cauſes Spiritual (which are more manifeſt, and eaſie to be diſcovered) are ſlightly ſought after, and ſo but little endeavour to remove them, hence no wonder that the Effect remains, we enquire in hypocriſie.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When we enquire, but 'tis without any deſire or willingneſs to ſee the <hi>true Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Cauſes,</hi> or b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> convinced of them, we enquire with a kinde of fore-ſtalled and prejudicate ſpirit; we have taken up already what our determination is and muſt be: hence this it is, and no other thing, hence we arm our ſelves with a reſolution to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand all Conviction, and ſo lay a block in the way to prevent any effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacious meeting God i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch a way as might remove his hand off from us, and prevent the proceſs of more and worſe miſeries.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When we enquire, but never intend to <hi>reform:</hi> this was the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe, <hi>Jer.</hi> 43. thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> promiſes were indeed fair, but when the Prophet had gone to God and enqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed for them, and throught
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:107003:32"/> them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord back again, now they diſcover their hypocritical heart, <hi>Chap<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 44. 16. they would make a formal kinde of proceſs, as if they had been deſirous of Gods counſel to direct them; and had the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer been to their mindes, what godly men might they have pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for: Hath God told <hi>us</hi> nothing? have not his Meſſengers pointed a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing? ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e not the very Providences themſelves given light to our enquiry? but all this while, where is the <hi>amendment?</hi> who turns from his evil way to the Lord?</p>
            <p n="5">5. When we enquire, but not of <hi>Gods Watchmen:</hi> times have been when they have been eſteemed, and looked upon as Watchmen indeed, who were beſt able to inform us in the Counſels of God; but now who more blinde then they in our practical judgement? a prejudicial eye is caſt upon them, and they laid by as uſeleſs. Oh how is the cavil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of an Anabaptiſtical and cenſorious ſpirit (who can ſpit his venom in the face of Magiſtracy and Miniſtry, and make theſe the Cauſes of all our Trouble) ſet by among many? whiles the faithful Warnings of Gods Servants are contemned.</p>
            <p n="6">6. When poſſibly we enquire of them, but with a <hi>ſlighty</hi> and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainful <hi>ſpirit:</hi> Oh how many go with their nice Queries to their Miniſters, when they deſpiſe them in their hearts? and either lay ſnares for them, as they dealt by Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Is it lawful to pay tribute,</hi> &amp;c? or at leaſt do not go to them as ſuch whom they do indeed look upon and eſteem to be ſent of God, and therefore may hopefully expect to receive better information from them, then from others; hence they little regard, and leſs do they practice.</p>
            <p n="7">7. When we enquire, but we are not willing the Cauſe ſhould be in <hi>our ſelves,</hi> but in others: and hence though we enquire with ſome earneſtneſs, yet if the Anſwer (though true) touch us, and our Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, we cannot bear it; this ſhews that we enquire with a cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious (which is an hypocritical) ſpirit: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> regard not how much blame be laid upon others, but are willing to take none of the blame and ſhame of the ſin to our ſelves; and therefore come not up to this, which is the onely ſincere firſt Enquiry, <hi>What have I done?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> II. To humble us for our hypocriſie upon this account: and how much cauſe the beſt of us may have to take the ſhame of this ſin upon us before God this day, if we did ſeriouſly enquire, we might in ſome meaſure diſcover: let us then bewail it ſeriouſly. For <hi>Motive:</hi> Conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:107003:33"/>1. It is no light matter to mock God; ſo we do in every act of hypocriſie: <hi>God is not mocked,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle; <hi>i. e.</hi> he will not be put off with, nor will he put up our mockeries.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God and <hi>your ſin will finde you out:</hi> God diſcerns the heart, and therefore it is no mocking of him; he is <hi>a jealous God,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he will make you to know how ill he takes it, he will ſmoke againſt your beſt ſervices, that you may underſtand your hypocriſie is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58. 1—</p>
            <p>Thus much of the <hi>Queſtion</hi> of the <hi>Idumeans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Anſwer</hi> of the Prophet follows. The Anſwer is <hi>ſhort and full.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Watchman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> i. e.</hi> the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah. Iſaiah</hi> owns his Office, though they put it upon him as a ſcoff and mockery, but he is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of it in the leaſt. Hence</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>The Miniſters of God are not aſhamed of their Office, though the world ſeem to deſpiſe and flout at it.</hi> Let the men of the world think never ſo undervaluingly of the Place and Work they are in, they yet prize and eſteem it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. Becauſe it is an Office inſtituted by God, and therefore will be defended, and vindicated by him: he owns them, though the world deſpiſe them, and he will take upon him to plead the Cauſe of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed Miniſters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. Becauſe it is a high and honourable Office, though deſpiſed: let the world look upon it with an eye of diſdain, yet it is in it ſelf a dignity, an honour: Miniſters <hi>are Ambaſſadors from God to men,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 20. now the Majeſty of the Prince is repreſented in the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, God looks that part of his own honour is engraven upon this Office, Miniſters therefore have no reaſon to be diſcouraged by the contumelies of the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 3. Becauſe it is a Work which is accompanied with the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous power of God, and made a means of the Salvation of Gods E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect: this is <hi>Pauls</hi> reaſon why <hi>he is not aſhamed of the Goſpel,</hi> Rom. 1. 16. When they ſee God putting forth his p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wer, and making the ſtouteſt ſinners fall (like the walls of <hi>Jericho</hi>) at the ſounding of the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Goſpel, and many ſouls by their Miniſtry brought effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally home to God, this is enough to make them diſdain the ſlanders and revilings of men, and glory in their Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 4. Becauſe <hi>its reward is with God:</hi> Miniſters look not for, nor would be ſatisfied with an earthly reward; <hi>their praiſe is of God, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:107003:34"/> not of men:</hi> he hath promiſed <hi>they ſhall not loſe their reward,</hi> and they dare truſt him, and can chearfully endure, and meet with all that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling and contempt which wicked men delight to be venting againſt them: the Crown will more then pay for all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Learn hence to have a care that you contemn not Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and above all the Office of the Miniſtry: doubtleſs the low eſteem of this great Work appearing by too many evident ſymptomes, is one thing for which God is now pleading with us, and therefore ſeaſonable at this time to be hinted to us. Oh beware of this ſin. Conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. If we deſpiſe them, we deſpiſe God, <hi>Luke</hi> 10. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. the Prince ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts all the affronts and indignities offered to his Ambaſſadors, to bear a proper reſpect to himſelf; and do you then think that God will hear it? <hi>Moſes</hi> may hold his peace, Gods Miniſters may pity and pray for you, yea will; but God will not ſuffer his own glory thus to be trampled upon, nor his Servants thus to be abuſed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If we contemn them, and receive not their Miniſtry, it is the ready way to be given up by God to a ſpirit of deluſion, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 10. Obſerve it, and you ſhall ſee, this hath been the door out of which ſo many have gone away into thoſe giddy diſtempers which they are now infected withall, even thoſe many Enthuſiaſms of the Devil; an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uing of the Miniſtry, an elevating and ſetting up private gifts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which hath led men by degrees to thoſe great Apoſtacies, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by their light (which would have ſhone clearly in its proper Orb) hath ſpent it ſelf in a blaze, and gone out in a ſtink<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng ſnuff.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Watchman ſaid] i. e.</hi> from God, and by his direction, we here ſee the Prophet gives them a ſerious Anſwer. Hence</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>What-ever end a people have in enquiring, it is the duty of Gods Miniſters faithfully to anſwer them according to the minde and counſel of God.</hi> See <hi>Jer.</hi> 42. 19, 20. the people they diſſembled, but <hi>Jeremiah</hi> tells them the truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. From the nature of their Office, which is to be <hi>Watchmen,</hi> which depends not upon the acceptance, or not acceptance of their Meſſage, but is an abſolute duty, whoſe neglect cannot be diſpenſed withall: whether they will hear or no, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> muſt diſcharge his Office, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. 7. yea, it lyes ſo upon him, as the neglect of it brings him under the dreadfull menaces of Gods wrath, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. 18. he breaks his charge if he neglect it, yea and hazards the undoing of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:107003:34"/> thoſe for whom he is ſet up to be a Watchman.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. Becauſe God will have a rebellious people left inexcuſeable, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 2. 5. though the prime end, and natural tendency of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, be for the Converſion and good of the people to whom they are ſent, yet God in juſt judgement will ſometimes have it to be to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe their Condemnation, and to make their miſery more dreadful: <hi>Line upon line,</hi> &amp;c. is ſometimes given to make a people <hi>ſtumble and fall, Iſa.</hi> 28. 13. all this is for Gods glory, the ſhine of the glory of his Juſtice, when he ſhall come to recover the honour of his deſpiſed Counſels and Warnings, and plead with a people for their wretched and inexcuſable violation of both Covenants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> I. See here a reaſon why Gods faithful Miniſters uſe ſo little humane policy in the execution of their Place and Office: ſhould they connive at our ſins, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ew pillows under our elbows, fawn upon us, or at the leaſt ſpeak in the dark and aloof off, they were moſt likely, in an eye of humane Reaſon, to live more quietly, and leſs hated: he is ready to be accounted our enemy who tells us the truth. How eaſily might they accommodate themſelves to humane affections, but they dare not do it, but ſpeak plain; not becauſe they are ignorant of the probability of what entertainment they are like to meet withall, but becauſe they dare not to be falſe to the charge and truſt which God hath laid upon them. I confeſs, concerning ſome things there may be an indiſcreet zeal, in theſe there is a time to hold one's peace; but in the diſcovery of the Counſels of God, and laying open crying ſins, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it's not the fear or favour of man, but the awful command of God, which muſt be, and is, the Rule of the ſerious Miniſter, who being ſent from God, muſt deliver his Embaſſie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> II. Learn hence how faithful God is to us, how unfaithful ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we be to him, and to our own ſouls: might we have our own deſires, we would hear nothing elſe but ſoothing and pleaſant words; he that preacheth ſin and wrath, is a Legalliſt, a <hi>Micaiah,</hi> he <hi>never ſpeaks good to us;</hi> thus would we go ſleeping and ſecure to Hell, run our ſelves jocundly into all miſery, ſuch enemies are we to our own ſouls: but how faithful is God, who ſeeing us falling into the ſeas of wrath, ſends to awaken us out of our ſleep, to tell us of our evil wayes, and to reclaim, and bring us back. That God hath ordained and ſet up the Office of the Miniſtry under that ſolemn and dreadful charge, As they will anſwer it in the great day, If they will not bring
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:107003:35"/> the guilt of the blood of ſouls upon their own heads, to tell ſinners of their wayes, and give them ſeaſonable and conſtant warning; herein is the Faithfulneſs of God, and his great Goodneſs wondrouſly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> III. Learn hence to account a plain-dealing Miniſtry to be of God, however they croſs our corruptions: if any in the world are indeed ſent of God to us, then ſurely thoſe, who laying aſide all ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ends and worldly intereſts, lay themſelves open to the hatred and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of the world, hazard to loſe our love and good will, to be evil ſpoken of, to ſuffer want, and hard uſage among us, rath then be ſilent in an evil day; rather then hold their peace, and let us alone in our ſins, or palliate and diſſemble with us in the Cauſe of God and our own ſouls. Pray to God that you may alwayes have and enjoy ſuch Miniſters, and that he would put this Spirit into his Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The morning cometh, and alſo the night</hi>] Here the Prophet anſwers them according to their particular enquiry about the ſucceſs. In which obſerve</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Conceſſion; <hi>The morning cometh:</hi> It is true indeed, you do for the preſent enjoy a ſeaſon of proſperity, though evil have been denounced againſt you; and it cometh ſtill, <hi>i. e.</hi> you have ſtill a ſhort ſeaſon behinde of day.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A Warning; <hi>and alſo the night:</hi> i. e. as you have your <hi>morning,</hi> ſo aſſure your ſelves you ſhall have your <hi>night;</hi> think not, nor deceive your ſelves into ſuch a fooliſh hope, as to promiſe your ſelves you ſhall never ſee adverſity, becauſe you now live at eaſe and proſper.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The words carry in them the face of an Argument: he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares their condition to a <hi>Natural day,</hi> in which there are two conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuting parts, <hi>viz. Day</hi> and <hi>Night, light</hi> and <hi>darkneſs,</hi> which naturally follow one upon another: the <hi>day</hi> of the people of God uſually (as the Natural day) begins with <hi>darkneſs,</hi> and ends in <hi>light;</hi> the wickeds day begins with <hi>morning,</hi> but ſhall end with <hi>night.</hi> Hence if they look for <hi>night</hi> to follow the cleareſt day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> why do they dream as if ſorrow could not come in the room of their preſent pleaſure and delight? Hence</p>
            <p>Doct. 1. <hi>God may afford a ſinning people; a people deſigned for wrath, a long morning of proſperity. Edoms Morning cometh,</hi> endureth a great while: God thus ſpared the <hi>Am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rites</hi> an hundred and fourty
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:107003:35"/> years, bare with the <hi>old World</hi> an hundred and twenty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. Becauſe this is the day of Gods forbearance: God is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly juſt, and he ſhall be known to be ſo in the day of vengeance, when the great Aſſizes ſhall be ſet, and he ſhall render unto every one according to their works; but mean while he hath a day of mercy, wherein (without any infringement to his Juſtice and Holineſs) he moderates the Sentence paſt upon ſinners, and delayes the fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, mean-while conferring much of his goodneſs upon them. Now the ſeaſon of the ſhine of this Attribute of Mercy, appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his Clemency and Benignity, is properly here in this world: God will have the glory of all his Attributes ſhine out and appear in his <hi>Efficiency;</hi> now there is no room for, nor knowledge of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, Long-ſufferance, and Goodneſs in Hell, where the Cup of Wrath is without mixture: God therefore now makes it <hi>appear in the veſſels of wrath fitted to deſtruction,</hi> Rom. 9. 22.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. Becauſe God hath in his Decrees, not onely laid men out for puniſhment, but for their meaſure and degrees of puniſhment, which they come to by the height of their ſin, and by the number of Mercies abuſed: this is an awful, but an undeniable Truth, That God hath not onely deſigned ſuch ſinners to deſtruction, but hath allotted them their place in Hell; <hi>Judas</hi> is gone to <hi>his place:</hi> there is a Hell more and leſs tolerable, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 15. as alſo that men come to this, by their abuſing and miſimproving of mercies, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 5. hence therefore ſinners muſt have ſuch a time of Patience, ſo many Mercies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> beyond which, as they ſhall not be ſpared, ſo before which they ſhall not be diſturbed, but ſet alone till their meaſure be fulfilled; till they are ripe, and fully fitted to deſtruction, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. 16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> I. Learn hence, that outward proſperity is no ſure token of Gods ſpecial favour, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9. 2. a perſon or people may have and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the worlds abundance, and over flow in the outward things of this life, and yet be the hated of God, ſuch whom God tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns like Oxen into a rich Paſture, where they may be fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed up for the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ughter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of Hell: reckon not therefore upon this. Have any of you eſcaped the common Calamities which God hath b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ging upon this Land? do not ſooth up your ſelves with this, and pleaſe your ſelves into an opinion that God loves you ever the better; a dear childe of God may be under the moſt ſever chaſtenings, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thou that art not chaſtiſed mayeſt be a ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tard.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:107003:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> II. This may call us all to a ſerious and ſolemn Examination of our ſelves, what uſe we have made of thoſe many dayes of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity which we have had: it is not enough that we have had them, but how have we improved them. Know it, the day of Reckoning is coming, and then an account will be taken, when the more any have received, the more they will have to anſwer for. We have been a people wonderfully favoured by the Lord, but let not this make us ſecure; who knows but we have turned Gods great Mercies into great Curſes by abuſing of them: 'tis time then (now God is coming to recover his Mercies out of our hands) to ask our own hearts, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we have not highly abuſed, yea ſo that if Repentance prevent not, to our final deſtruction.</p>
            <p>Doct. 2. <hi>A people in the very height of outward proſperity, may be very near to ruine and deſtruction.</hi> The Prophet ſpeaks here quick, as of ſudden Changes, <hi>The morning comes, alſo the night;</hi> intimating, as if there ſhould be no long diſtance between their morning and night, as if it ſhould be a ſhort morning, a day ſoon changed into night. You remember how it was with the <hi>Old World,</hi> and with <hi>Sodom,</hi> who were taken in the height of their pleaſures, in the top of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, and ſuddenly brought to a final end, and fearful deſolation; and our Saviour Chriſt ſpeaks of ſuch times in the dayes of the Goſpel, <hi>Luke 17. 26, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. Becauſe ſuch dayes ripen men faſter for deſtruction, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 22. the more men have, and abuſe, the deeper they run into Gods debt-book, the larger accounts they have: the better the Paſture is, the ſooner the Ox is fat; now you know the Ox is not taken from his Paſture, till ſuch time as the day of ſlaughter comes, hence God takes men in their height, and makes them come down wonderfully.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. From the nature of Patience, which as it can bear and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure a great deal, and a long while, ſo when it once comes to be worn out, and provoked, breaks forth into a moſt ſudden and di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eful flame: <hi>Laeſa patientia fit furor; Jer.</hi> 4. 4. That anger which is not ſuddenly and ſpeedily ſtirred up, when kindled is moſt furious and unappeaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 3. From the nature of ſin, which the more goodneſs of God it enjoyes, the more it heightens it ſelf into boldneſs and violence: <hi>Sodoms fulneſs</hi> (which called to glorifie God) was an occaſion of the <hi>crying ſins</hi> that were among them; hence they pull down wrath, and there is no remedy.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:107003:36"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> This may convince us of a great deal of the Goodneſs and rich Mercy of God expreſſed to us-ward in this very thing, in that he hath not brought our Calamity and Deſolation on us all at once, but hath come by degrees, he hath not dealt with us as with <hi>Sodom,</hi> whoſe deſolation came in a day, ſudden as a Whirlwind; whoſe morning was fair and clear, who ſaw the Sun ſhine upon them, the ſame day wherein they were overwhelmed with a ſtorm of Fire and Brimſtone. Our Sun hath been obſcured, our day brought to the twilight, before ſudden and thick darkneſs: theſe are tokens of Gods long ſuffering and great favour towards us; hereby God gives us further warning, and more ſpace to repent. Oh let us then make this uſe of it; God ſhews by this that he is willing to be ſtopt in his way, to accept the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ifices of an humble ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Doct 3. <hi>God would have us in the Morning to think of Night.</hi> Whiles times of peace and plenty continue, God would that we bethink our ſelves of a change, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11. 8. God would have theſe <hi>Edomites</hi> to conſider that <hi>Night</hi> would come after their <hi>Morning</hi> was over.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> From the ſutableneſs and ſeaſonableneſs of theſe thoughts at ſuch a time.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The ſerious conſideration of it may be a means to prevent it: by <hi>removing the Cauſe, the Effect ceaſeth,</hi> God brings ſorrow for ſin, Repentance ſtops him in his courſe, and brings back his favour. A wiſe and holy improvement of the day of Gods goodneſs and favour, cauſeth the Sun to ſtand ſtill in our Firmament, and the day of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity to laſt: but the ſinful abuſe of it haſtens the ſetting of our Sun, and coming of the black and dark night; now to think of this beforehand, affords us a ſolemn and awakening Motive carefully to improve our time of viſitation, whereby we may enjoy a bleſſed lengthening out of our tranquillity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The due improving of theſe thoughts may be a means to fit us for the <hi>Night:</hi> Fore-warned (as we ſay) and fore-armed; the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of ſtorms and tempeſts, drives perſons to ſeek a ſeaſonable ſhelter and hiding-place from the wind and rain: this makes ſerious ſouls prepare <hi>to meet with their God.</hi> They that never think nor conſider o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a change, never think of being <hi>emptied from veſſel to veſſel,</hi> are like <hi>fiſhes taken in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n evil <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> are horribly unprepared; but the ſerious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of dayes of Calamity, will drive us (if any thing) to make our peace with God, to take up our ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er under the wings of the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:107003:37"/> Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that the evil of theſe evils overtake us not.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Theſe thoughts will make us wiſe to improve our <hi>morning</hi> to the beſt advantage: when we ſee night coming, and a great deal before us to do, this doubles our diligence, whiles many times we idle away much of the day, as long as we think it a great while to night; as long as we apprehend the Sun to be in its height, we ſleep, but when it is near ſetting, then we redeem the time. Oh how laborious Chriſtians ſhould we be, how ſedulous in the work of God, if we did but carry along with us in our mindes the thoughts of the <hi>evil day,</hi> did we but with a cautious expectation every day look for a change!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> I. See here how grievouſly they provoke God, who in the day of their proſperity minde nothing but their eaſe and pleaſure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Amos</hi> 6. 1—it is an iniquity which God cannot bear, as follows in the ſequel: it is a note of a <hi>wicked man,</hi> when he enjoyes the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of God, to do nothing but ſpend his dayes in mirth; there are <hi>the afflictions of Joſeph</hi> to minde, yea alſo and our own change to minde: what was the ground of <hi>Jeruſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ms</hi> deſtruction but this? <hi>Lam.</hi> 1. 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> II. This may be for <hi>Direction</hi> to us, what uſe to make of the conſideration and fore-thoughts of the <hi>night of Trouble,</hi> in a few things:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Conſider what juſt reaſon we have to expect <hi>a night,</hi> a change, more ſorrows ſtill; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The grievous loſs of precious time in the beſt. Oh how much of our time here have we waſted away, <hi>aliud agendo,</hi> in that which profits not. None in the world ever enjoyed a happier advantage to ſerv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God in, then we have done for ſo long a ſeaſon in this Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, wherein we have enjoyed peace, and the liberties of the Goſpel, liberty to be as good as we will, and all encouragements to ſerve God; but oh how much have we been waſting away unprofitably, in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, and buſie Wranglings about matters of an inferious conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, about our worldly Cares and Perplexities, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We have uſed but little care to redeem thoſe precious hours from thoſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſing vanities which beſet us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hainous provocations of Gods wrath in many, which may make God ſay of us as of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that <hi>we preſs him as a Cart is preſſed with the ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aves.</hi> Oh how many crying ſins have been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound among us? Should God come and plead with us, (and indeed ſo he doth, and hath
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:107003:37"/> been pleading with us a great while) and reade over to u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Bill o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our ſeveral <hi>Items,</hi> how few need he leave out of thoſe drawn up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in that heavy Accuſation recorded <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22. 14. I need not mention in particular, Crying ſins have been found, and are prevailing, and ſhall not God viſit for theſe things? will he not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged on ſuch a people, who promiſed, and gave him hopes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things?</p>
            <p>Secondly, Conſider what Warnings God hath given us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the <hi>Miniſtry:</hi> Hath it not been the voice of God in the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th of all his Prophets, hath there not been a full and univerſal conſent of all Gods Meſſengers, that <hi>God hath a Contr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>verſie with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> people, and cannot be ſilent?</hi> How long hath this been a Concluſion, and they have been faithful to diſcharge their duty, and acquit their Conſciences on this account by declaring it: this we have heard often proclaimed, and by ſound demonſtration cleared t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> us, but we have made too light of that, Miniſters muſt ſay ſomething to keep up their credit, and keep the people in awe. And therefore</p>
            <p n="2">2. God hath warned us in his <hi>Providences,</hi> that ſo he might make us believe his Word in the mouth of his Meſſengers: and that no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> only by many Signs and Prognoſticks, uſual for erunners of calamitous times, but alſo by the <hi>Vaunt-C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rriers</hi> of his Army of Judgements<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> beginnings of ſorrows; many have been the ſad and awakening Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences of theſe latter years, he is a ſtranger in our <hi>Iſrael</hi> who is unacquainted therewithall. If we will not credit the Word, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> let us believe the Rod; if in the <hi>Morning</hi> we have been eaſily del<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed into falſe and vain hopes, to think it would never be <hi>Night,</hi> yet one would think, when the Sun ſeems to be ſetting in our Horizon, and the dus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the Evening is coming upon us, we ſhould now be ready to give credit to it, unleſs we are fallen into a Lethargi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and dead ſleep o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Security.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Now let us bethink our ſelves how it may be prevented: to what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſhould we be warned, but that we might endeavour to preven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and eſcape the drinking the dregs of this Cup, whereof we have been already made to ſip?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Believe that God is yet willing to be ſtop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, he ſhews how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> be is to afflict, and therefore is ready to be ſtayed. God loves to be hindred in theſe proceedings, he himſelf looks to ſee if there be <hi>any to ſtand in the gap, and make up the brea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h,</hi> and he <hi>is gri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ved when
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:107003:38"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an finde none:</hi> this is encouragement; <hi>The God of Iſrael is a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> God,</hi> and will be ready to ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>end that mercy to us, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any advantage he hath in his hand againſt us: he therefore (when in the midſt of Judgements) ſwears, that he <hi>delights not in the ſinners death,</hi> and calls upon them to return to him, <hi>Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k.</hi> 36 11.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Improve the means of prevention that are appointed by God: as there is a poſſibility of ſtopping the proceſs of Gods wrath, ſo there is but one onely way whereby it can be done, and that is by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning by a thorow Repentance, by a confeſſing and forſaking thoſe ſins that pull down wrath; we muſt <hi>confeſs,</hi> that he may be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged Juſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we muſt <hi>forſake,</hi> becauſe the Cauſe muſt be taken away before the Effect ceaſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Prepare that if the <hi>Night</hi> come you may make advantage of it for your good: though the Night hath many ſad diſadvantages, yet it hath its advantages too; though it pay the ſluggard with ſhame, yet to him that hath done his work, 'tis ſweet, and helps his reſt: if it finde you <hi>in a way of righteouſneſs,</hi> it can do you no hurt, it ſhall do you a great deal of good. Oh prepare, get your ſins p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rdoned and done away, if the guilt of theſe remain, they will interpoſe as a thick and diſmall Cloud, between the light of Gods countenance and your ſouls, then it will be a black and dark night indeed: get into Chriſt, make him your ſhelter and rock, he is a ſure refuge, and the tempeſt cannot break through him to do you any harm, though it ſhould bear down, and waſh away the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lay houſe of your earthly tabernacle,</hi> yet it cannot keep you from, but will haſten you to a more ſpeedy poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of your Eternal Manſion, your houſe of reſt, <hi>whoſe builder and maker is God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If ye will enquire, enquire ye:</hi>] The Prophet having anſwered their <hi>Queſtion</hi> about the Events of Providence, and confirmed his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warnings, by taking off the objection from preſent proſperity, and aſcertained them of the haſtening of their Calamity; being deſirous to prevent their utter deſolation, addes a word of ſerious advice to them from God, wherein he tacitly reproves the hypocriſie of their former inquiſitiveneſs, and calls up to ſincerity in their enquiring<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Hence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct. 1. <hi>Hypocritical ſervice is in God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> account no ſervice. Edom</hi> makes a ſeeming enquiry, but they did it not in earneſt; hence the Prophet ſpeaks of it as no enquiry at all. The <hi>Jews</hi> faſted much, and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:107003:38"/> were angry that God did not anſwer them, that their affliction ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained on them; God tells them he looked upon it as no Faſt, <hi>Iſai,</hi> 58. 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> is, B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cauſe it</p>
            <p n="1">1. Comes not from a right principle; Grace, which onely can do any thing acceptably to God: where there is not this, the Sacrifice is an abomination. That which hath the matter of viſible ſervice in it, is looked upon as the greateſt ſin, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66 2.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Is not done in a right manner, <hi>viz.</hi> Sincerity of heart. God requires the heart in every ſervice, for that commands all the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and what way that goes, thither indeed all aim; hence the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint is, <hi>Their heart was not upright toward God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Neither doth it aim at the right end, <hi>viz.</hi> the glory of God: this is the end of all true ſervice, to bring glory to our Maker, and if this be not our aim and end, God is not indeed ſerved in it. Now every hypocritical ſervice wants all theſe ingredients, and therefore is not a ſerving of God, hence no wonder if he do not accept it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> This may be for Tryal, to ſee whether our ſervices and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries have not been hypocritical, whether or no we have not drawn <hi>near to God with our lips, whiles our hearts have been far from him:</hi> Surely there is great reaſon why we ſhould make ſuch an enquiry as this is, if we conſider what effect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have followed upon our faſtings.</p>
            <p n="1">1. How little fruit of Reformation hath there been on our part: what one thing hath there been amended? what publick ſin hath been reclaimed? is there ever the leſs vanity, pride, profaneneſs, oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, contention? or do not theſe and the like evils ſeem rather to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and grow more after all? and is not this a note of hypocriſie, to confeſs, and ſeem to bewail, and yet not to amend, but grow worſe?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Wherein hath there been a removal of the Rod on Gods part: do not our calamities ſeem to increaſe, and the ſtroke to be more and more heavy? we loſt many Inſtruments of the glory of God, and ſuffered many bodily Calamities, and Blaſtings of our labours, and we have faſted; but <hi>his anger is not turned a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay, but his hand is ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out ſtill;</hi> yea more varieties of ſorrows are heaped upon us: we may therefore well examine our own hearts, what is the reaſon of all this, unleſs we have no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yet indeed turned to him who ſmote us, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lord our God.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:107003:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Doct. 2. <hi>Whatſoever pretence we make, yet God knows with what hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> come to him, to ask counſel and direction from him.</hi> The <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t</hi> ſeem earneſt and urgent, but yet the Lord tells them that they make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one (<hi>i. e.</hi> no acceptable) enq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> From his Omniſcience, <hi>Pſal. 94. 8. Heb.</hi> 4. 13. he is the heart maker, and therefore hath the power of diſcerning the heart, and all the motions and turnings of it; all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ooks and corners of it are open: it is ſo full of deceitfulneſs, that we cannot know it throughly, but he perfectly and exactly views, and diſcerns it; if he did not know the ſecre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of our hearts, if any thing were hid from him, he were not God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Learn hence that you cannot deceive God, man you may put off with fine words and fair pretences, but not ſo God: hath not God made it to appear that he will not be mocked by us? we have offered up to him hypocritical ſervices, and accordingly we have been p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id: we come with an Idol in our heart, and he hath anſwered us according to our Idol. Let us then look to our ſelves, and beware how we com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> before him, with what heart we come into his preſence: know it, if <hi>we ſow wind, we ſhall reap the eaſt-wind;</hi> we may think to deceive and put him off with ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mock<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ies, but he obſerves and takes notice even of thoſe thoughts, and will make us to ſee and feel that he is d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſpleaſed with them: <hi>Bring</hi> then <hi>no more vain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>blations,</hi> offer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p no more heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſacrifices to him, but come loathing our ſelves, taking the true ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me of our ſins, and with a real deſire to be rid of them, and we ſhall be accepted.</p>
            <p>Doct. 3. <hi>Thoſe that would be inſtructed by God, in the gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nds of his quarrel, and means of reſtitution, muſt enquire in good earneſt.</hi> God loves not this hypocriſie, and if we bring it, he will anſwer accordingly, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14 4. God may indeed anſwer thoſe that enquire in hypocriſie, but it is an unwelcome anſwer he gives them, <hi>viz.</hi> a confirmation, and a ratifying of his Threatnings, and an aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rance of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e fulfilling of them: All the news that <hi>Edom</hi> hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, is, That their <hi>Night</hi> ſhall come on them, the evil determined ſhall be brought to paſs againſt them: bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God gives an anſwer of peace onely to thoſe that enquire in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſ.</hi> 1. Becauſe this hypocriſie is one great reaſon of the conti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> anger, and therefore muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> before God w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ccept of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s when we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to enquire of him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:107003:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> had ſinned, and God had afflicted; they had faſted, and God had added to their affliction, and they now would know a reaſon of this: why, the iniquity of their faſting procured them this; <hi>Is this ſuch a Faſt as I have required?</hi> hence God direct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them how to faſt aright, in the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quel. <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dah</hi> had been full of viſible ſervices, but God was wrath, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. he tells them how they ſhould come and reaſon out the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſe with him, and enjoy pardon and mercy at his hands, <hi>ver.</hi> 16, 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. Becauſe there can be no hope of true Reformation, where there is not ſincerity in the enquiring: if we enquire hypocritically, we cannot intend really to repent; for the very firſt ſtep to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, is a ſerious ſearch and enquiry into our hearts and wayes, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. 40. Thoſe proud men, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. they come in hypocriſie, and hence when they have an anſwer from God, and are counſelled for their good, they take up a reſolution that they will not do according to the word of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> I. for <hi>Tryall:</hi> Let us examine whether this be not the reaſon why God hath not yet made us to ſee, and be ſenſible of the grounds of his Conteſt with this poor Land. This is the great and general complaint, We have faſted and prayed, ſought and enquired, but his hand is ſtretched out ſtill, and he is yet pleaſed to hide the reaſon from us, and not to let us know why he contendeth with us. Oh, do not charge God fooliſhly of injury or hard de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ling: God, though he be Soveraign, and <hi>not bound to give an account of any of his matters,</hi> yet he is a gracious God, and vouchſafes to the humble ſoul to make a diſcovery of his Counſels, would we know why God hides his mind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from us; look upon our ſelves, did we ever yet enquire in good ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt? Gods hand hath been heavy on this account upon us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In ſome things God hath divided the Apprehenſions of his Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as is too manifeſt and apparent; and this is your t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>umph, which ought to be your ſorrow, for if in any point <hi>the Trumpet give a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> uncertain found,</hi> yours is the ſuffering like to be, and yet this is a general out-cry, <hi>What do you expect from us? what do you think we ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, when our Miniſters are not yet agreed.</hi> Well, it is a humbling thought, but do not w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ands, and wipe your mouthes, as if you were clean in this point, but be humbled, you may finde the roo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and cauſe of the affliction in your ſelves; if you ſought God in good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt for your Miniſters, and ſo prayed for them as you ought to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ſerio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>egged of God to give them one hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> there would be a great<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t among them.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:107003:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>2. In other things there is a general Conſent and Agreement among Gods Miniſters, but the people of God are divided in apprehenſion: and hence a check in many places put to the comfortable carrying on of the Work of Reformation; ſome are of one minde, ſome of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; ſome conſent with, and other diſſent from the Meſſengers of God, and hence are ready to charge each other mutually as the cauſes of our Calamity: and what's the reaſon of theſe <hi>diviſions in Reuben,</hi> but that we have enquired of God with an Idol in our hearts? We firſt take up Concluſions that we are in the right, and all others out of the way that are d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fferent from us; and then, with theſe Concluſions we go to God, and make as if we enquired of him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In other things all agree as to the Theory, <hi>viz.</hi> as to many Moral Cauſes and Occaſions, which are juſtly provo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing to God to bring a Scourge upon us: Who agrees not that Pride, Profaneneſs, Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are things which provoke Gods anger, and cauſe him to ſmoke againſt a people in the fire of his diſpleaſure? yea, who agrees not that theſe ſins are prevailing and increaſing among us? and yet we little reform theſe things in our ſelves, neither are we ſatisfied in our enquiry, but ſtill remain queriſts; and why? we ſtill enquire hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritically: this may be matter of humiliation this day, among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers let us not forget to bewail this ſin in the preſence of God, and beg of him to give us grace to ſeek him ſo as we may be heard by him, and he found by us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> II. for <hi>Exhortation:</hi> We come this day humbly to ask of God what his minde is, why he is offended at his people, and ſeems to be unwilling to be pacified, and to be angry at our requeſts; why, <hi>if you will enquire, enquire:</hi> if you would be ſatisfied, and receive an anſwer of peace at Gods hands, come in good earneſt, and God ſhall ſatisfie you this day: none ever asked counſel of him with a true and ſincere heart, but was ſatisfied. For your help herein by way of Direction in this great buſineſs, if you would receive help and counſell from God, then</p>
            <p n="1">1. Lay down your own judgements and wills at the foot of God, there are many that bring a fore-ſtalled judgement, and will (as we heard) take up their raſh Concluſions, according to their o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and reſolve never to be moved from them: this provokes God to leave us up to be ſeduced by our own deluſions. Empty your ſelves therefore of your own wiſdome and will, that you may be ready to entertain his.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:107003:40"/>
            <p>2. Make the Word of God your Rule of enquiry, make that your Light and Lamp to lead you in your ſearch after the Cauſes of Gods diſpleaſure: go not by humane policy, or carnal reaſon, or other mens judgements and apprehenſions, which are fallacious; no, <hi>let God be true, and every man a lyar.</hi> Compare we our ſelves by his Word exactly, by the Rule, and by Examples, and let Conſcience be an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Judge, and doubtleſs we ſhall diſcover more then a little.</p>
            <p n="1">3. Come with an humble heart, prepared to ſubmit to whatſoever God ſhall diſcover. Conſider, many things have been told you, but they have met with, and croſt your corruptions, and ſo you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected them: a proud heart is never like to be ſo familiar with God as to be inſtructed by him, he ſees ſuch at a diſtance: would you have God to teach you, ſubmit humbly to his teaching.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If the ſin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all upon you in particular, be ready to take the ſhame of it: if while thou art ſtanding before God, asking him by whom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and for what he is provoked? if he anſwer, <hi>Thou art the man,</hi> for theſe and thoſe things he is provoked and offended; why, now <hi>lay thy mouth in the duſt,</hi> reply not againſt him. While the ſin is laid upon others, and it toucheth not us, as we conceive, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at leaſt onely our natural infirmities, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we are well pleaſed; but when our ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>res come to be opened, rubbed and chafed, why then we kick, and fling, and rage, and grow mad. Avoid this frame, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear patiently to be laid open and reproved.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the Command laid upon you be never ſo croſs, be ready and willing to obey it: it may be, that which God expects may be exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing averſe, an Opinion which thou haſt been long rooted and rivetted in, and dwelt upon with great confidence; a ſin which hath brought thee in a great deal of profit, credit, or the like: the thing which God commands may ſeem to carnal Reaſon unreaſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> now a proud heart will fling away; but have a care thou bring not ſuch an heart before the great <hi>Searcher of hearts:</hi> Come, able in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſincerely to ſay, <hi>Speak Lord, thy Servant heareth; Command me what th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> wilt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I am ready to obey and follow thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. Begin at home in your enquiry: be ſure ſearch your own hearts in the firſt place, whether the <hi>Acha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> the <hi>troubler of Iſrael</hi> be not lodg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in your own breaſt. We keep a great deal of do abroad, ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, enqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing, cenſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as if we were true men to God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to find out the ſin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but we are like ſome treacherous Conſtable,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:107003:41"/> that hath a Warrant to ſearch for a Malefactor, he is very buſie and ſtrict in his Office, ſearcheth and ranſacks every houſe in the Town, pries into every corner, as very deſirous to fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de him out, and bring him forth, and yet mean while he lyes hid at home in his own houſe: Oh! this will never do, if thou knoweſt any ſin harboured in thy heart, lie not to God by thus enquiring, nay if thou do but ſuſpect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, let that be enough to cauſe a ſearch: and to that end examine all thy wayes and actions, and ſee whether they have not been provoking to God; examine them throughly.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the matter of them, ſee whether thou haſt not fallen ſhort in many things of the letter of the Law, committed thoſe very ſins, neglected thoſe very d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ties, which the leaſt light of Conſcience might have convinced thee to be thy duty to be done or avoided.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the Circumſtance of thy actions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of <hi>time,</hi> a thing beautiful in its ſeaſon; unſeaſonable, is ugly and deformed: haſt thou taken the ſeaſons of Chriſtian duties? haſt thou ſpoken againſt thy neighbours ſins plainly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to his face; privately, or not rather behinde his back, ſlanderouſly reviling him, <hi>&amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">2. Of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> or <hi>perſons: David</hi> would <hi>hold his tongue in preſence of the wicked;</hi> how many times haſt thou failed of due conſideration, when, or before thou haſt thus done, or thus ſaid.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the <hi>manner</hi> of the carriage of your ſelves: it may be you have for the <hi>matter</hi> attended your duty, but have you for the <hi>manner</hi> too? have not you run out of your duty, and run into ſin upon this account? have you not under pretext of zeal for Gods glory, and upholding his Name and Honour, given the reins into the neck of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> paſſions, and with <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpoken unadviſedly; yea worſe then he, raged, reviled, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> Examine every thing, and poſſibly God may diſcover to you more of this miſchief lodged in your own heart, then ever yet you were aware of.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But general viſitations, argue a general pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vocation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they argue that we muſt look abread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Objection hath nothing in it to impair the neceſſity of the duty urged in the Direction, at ſuch a time as this: for,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sometimes a private perſon may be the occaſion of a general and publick Calamity: <hi>Acha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> is <hi>the diſturber of Iſrael; Iſrael</hi> is charged with his ſin, and <hi>fly before their enemies:</hi> we reade of nothing elſe that the Lord charges upon them, but onely his ſin.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:107003:41"/>2. General is made up of particulars, and thou art one of thoſe particulars, and therefore mayeſt well examine thy ſelf upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of publick and general viſitations. If every one ſhould ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe themſelves, where ſhould the ſin be found? God ſaith, <hi>In thee are found ſuch, &amp;c.</hi> Ezek. 22. he doth not there lay every particular ſin upon all, yet all theſe went together to make up the provocation of Gods wrath, and procure their publick Calamity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thou it may be art a private perſon, and therefore canſt do but little upon a publick account but by thy prayers; labour therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o do the more with thine own heart. God hath not ſet every man in ſuch a place, wherein he is called to buſie himſelf in matters of publick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, theſe belong to perſons in publick employment, whom we can onely aſſiſt by our prayers, or a detection and diſcovery of ſuch particular enormities as we are privy to, that they may receive their due reward, and ſin may be taken out of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> but we have the more ſcope and opportunity to be ſearching our own hearts, and if we neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect that work, we do little or nothing.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Thou art not fitted to look abroad, till thou haſt firſt made a thorough work at home, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 1—Thou art like to make but poor work in publick matters, whiles thou harboureſt ſin in thine own heart; if therefore thou haſt a deſire to do God ſervice upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, thou hadſt need to be more then ordinarily careful to clear thy own accounts with God, leſt thou be found guilty of hypocriſie. It will be found the ready way to bring thy ſelf under inexcuſable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation before God, to ſearch after and condemn thoſe ſins in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which thou thy ſelf liveſt in the daily practice of, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 1. thou muſt therefore prepare thy ſelf to this work by a thorough ſearch of thy own heart.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Particular Repentance goes before general mercies, <hi>Zech.</hi> 11. 9. if God intend good to this poor Land he will bring us to this, he will make us get alone, and every one lay his finger upon his own ſore, and mourn over our ſins wherewithall we have been provoking his Majeſty: and when he hath once brought us to that, the time of his gracious viſitation is near at hand; yea, that indeed is the firſt great mercy, for which let us this day ſeek his face.</p>
            <p>5. Reform according to thy ability, and where thou canſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, there mourn.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Reform according to thy latitude.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:107003:42"/>1. Reform thy own ſoul by due diſcipline towards it, here thou canſt not be too ſtrict and ſevere; let the ſearch be thorough, and the reformation univerſal: mortifie thy luſts and corruptions, ranſack and cleanſe every corner of thy heart, let none of thy Idols remain, but put them all away; reſolve with <hi>Ephraim,</hi> that thou wilt have no more to do with them, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14. 8. and beg of God grace that thou mayeſt ſtand to thy reſolutions.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Reform others that are under thy charge, as far as thou canſt do thy beſt; ſay to thy Children, as <hi>Jacob</hi> to his ſons, <hi>Put away every one from among you his ſtrange gods: Joſhua,</hi> you know, could under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take not onely for himſelf, but for his too, <hi>I and my houſe will ſerve the Lord:</hi> be ſure to reform them as to the outward man, you can indeed do no more, but be ſure do that. Content not your ſelves to give them ſome ſlighty reproofs for their ſins, that was <hi>Eli</hi>'s ſin, which removed his family from the Prieſthood, but make uſe of that authority which God hath put into your hands, as occaſion may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, and then commend the ſucceſs to God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Pray to God that he would</p>
            <p n="1">(1) Give and continue an endeavour after Reformation to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy and Miniſtry, and give them an advantage, and encourage them in that Work. Bleſs God in as much as you ſee their hearts towards the Work, beg of him that he would remove all obſtacles and hindrances out of the way, that there may be a thorough and glorious Work of it. Oh be earneſt with God for this, without it we have but little hopes to ſee any more good dayes.</p>
            <p n="2">(2) Give a ſpirit of Reformation to all his people, that ſuch a work may be univerſall conſented to, that we may all ſet our hearts and ſhoulders to the Work: doubtleſs there is no greater good we can beg for at the hands of God at this time.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Where thou canſt do no good, there mourn: beg of God to give thee a ſpirit of mourning for all the ſins of the Land. We finde this ſpirit to have been eminent in good <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 119. 136, 158 and it is that, which (if it tend not to the prevention of publick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>) will bring a private bleſſing along with it, ſuch ſhall not be forgotten in the day of Calamity, but be noted for mercy, <hi>Ezek</hi> 9. 4.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Let thy further enquiry be accomparied with amendment of what is at the preſent diſcovered, that is the way to know more; to be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:107003:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> in a little, is the way to be truſted with more. If I miſtake not, I have now my finger upon the right Sore. I may ſay indeed this is <hi>New Englands</hi> great diſeaſe; God hath begun in his Judgements to viſit us, and there is a great deal of enquiry after the Cauſe: Gods Miniſters endeavour faithfully to diſcover it, and yet ſtill we are queriſts; Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence ſpeaks, and points at many things evidently, and ſtill we are where we were; we acknowledge many things, and grant them to be amiſs, and yet ſtill the cry is, <hi>What's the reaſon?</hi> God is pleaſed to hide the reaſon: and why? why, men cannot ſee wood for trees: if we wait for immediate Revelations, we may wait long e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, there is no expecting of one to come from the dead to tell us. Indeed we can hardly look any where, but we may ſee cauſes apparent.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let every private perſon look at home, take an account with his own heart, and he ſhall ſee enough to mend there. Out of doubt, if we deal here ingenuouſly, we ſhall finde that which may teach us to juſtifie God, and declare him righteous in what concerns us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Look into Families, and fee what diſorders there are, Children riſing up againſt Parents, and carrying themſelves diſobediently, which hath a dreadful Curſe denounced againſt it: Parents neglecting the due care of their Children, to <hi>nurture and bring them up in the admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord,</hi> cockering, and making them their equals, not keeping their due diſtances, and too many families without the Worſhip of God in them, being more like Pagan, then Chriſtian houſes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Look into Towns, and there you ſhall ſee diſorders, young <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> deſpiſing the aged, and carrying themſelves contemptuouſly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them; vanity and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> abounding; a ſelfiſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> upon the moſt, together with a neglect of one another <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that love which is due one to another wholly in many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; Town-Societies rent in pieces with diſorderly Contention.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Look into Congregations, and there you ſhall ſee confuſions; ſome contending with their Miniſters, and others biting and catching at one another; ſome not agreeing about the ſetting up of the Of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ances of God among them, and others not contented when they have them, but pulling them down again with might and main; great emulations, jealouſies, falſe ſurmiſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Miniſters deſpiſed, their Office queſtioned, their Authority caſt off, and trampled upon, then perſons undervalued and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their comfortable Supply and Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance neglected, Ordinances <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> frequented with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:107003:43"/>5. Look into the Body Politick, or Civil State, and there you ſhall ſee the Sinews of our Civil Society wondrouſly looſened: the want of Power in the Supreme Repreſentative Body to ſtrengthen them, by reaſon of the neceſſary evils incident to a declining Popular Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; and hence ariſe many misbehaviours, which time forbids to mention.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Look into the Body Eccleſiaſtical, and there you ſhall ſee Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; ſome ready to exalt themſelves above the Civil Magiſtrate, and diſowning his Civil Power in matters appertaining to Godlineſs; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ready to renounce Confociation and Communion one with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and many the like: and yet we ſtill enquire, <hi>What's the reaſon? Why is God diſpleaſed?</hi>—Why, is all this nothing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yes ſure: why, who knows not that theſe are our diſtempers?</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But there is ſome particular thing which muſt be known, and this is either in Magiſtrate, or Miniſters, or both: when ſhall you finde in Scripture that God ever brought publick Judgements on his people, but the ſins of Princes, Prieſts and Prophets were the cauſes of it, and are ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to have been? and therefore we muſt enquire yet further.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. This Objection is ſtrange and impertinent, it is as if a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician ſhould come to a perſon all over full of mortal wounds, and yet neglects them all, and ſtrangely cries out, There is one ſingular wound which I muſt finde out: is not this to ſuffer the perſon wilfully to periſh, by letting him bleed out his life at the known wounds, while he goes upon the diſcovery of one unknown? Is not this <hi>New-Englands</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuch as was once <hi>Judahs,</hi> Iſa. 1. 5. and ſhall we yet grope as in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> after ſome ſingular thing: I therefore fear that this is but a fond and hypocritical excuſe, to put off the edge of the conviction of preſent ſins, and keep up our credit too, as if we would willingly know the minde of God. But</p>
            <p n="2">2. Suppoſe there be ſome ſingular ſin: yet</p>
            <p>Firſt, It doth not need preſently terminate upon the Magiſtracy and Miniſtry, though wherein they may be wanting in their places, the Lord give them to ſee &amp; reform it, but it is not my work to ſcandalize thoſe who cannot hear me ſpeak: yet I ſay the ſin is not needfully theirs. But
<list>
                  <item>1. It may be univerſal, a ſpreading and over-running diſtemper. It is true indeed, God ſometimes ſpeaks to theſe, <hi>For your ſakes they ſhall go into captivity;</hi> but if we be wiſe and compare Scripture, we ſhall elſwhere hear God ſaying, <hi>My people would have it ſo:</hi> there is a concurtence, a delight in it.</item>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:107003:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <item>2. It may be a ſin which Magiſtrates and Miniſters would fain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, but we will not be reformed: our Form of Government both in Church and Commonwealth, is partly <hi>Democraticall,</hi> whoſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and degeneracy being <hi>Anarchy,</hi> the guilt of the errours of Adminiſtration fall upon the people, eſpecially if perſons in Office and Place do their endeavour to rectifie and amend them, but are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered; nay, though they attain an outward Reformation, yet there may remain the guilt of that ſin unrepented of upon a Land, which God will not forget, but (though he may delay for a while) will finde out a time to call to reckoning. <hi>Joſiah</hi> was the greateſt Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer in <hi>Judah</hi> that ever was, yet though there were peace in his time, Reade 2 <hi>Kings 22. 15. &amp;</hi> 23. 25, 26.</item>
                  <item>3. Conſider (though I ſpeak not to excuſe ſin in any, where they may be guilty before God) yet conſider why hath God lately taken away ſo many of his precious Servants in the Miniſtry, it is not to their damage or wrong, they are gone to their reſt, have left a ſinful and ſorrowful world, to be inveſted with a Crown of Glory, and to be with Chriſt, which is beſt: but we are bereaved, the Lights are put out of our Candleſticks; they were deſpiſed here, and they are now received to honour and glory: and this may call us to ſolemn conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Conſider <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57. 1—</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Be it a ſingular ſin, and let it center where it will, it ſeems we are to ſeek about it; I tell you, the way to know it, is to reform what we do know. God reveals himſelf by degrees to a people, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their improvement. God hath told us of theſe and thoſe things; why ſhould he diſcover any more, ſince we mend not, but make ſo ill uſe of what he hath diſcovered. Let me tell you, and I can aſſure you of it to be a truth, prove it, and you ſhall have experience of it, If we repent from our hearts of our known ſins, God will either remove the ſtroke off from us, or further diſcover what is provoking to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Return, come.] Verba feſtinantes.</hi> The words</p>
            <p n="1">1. Contain a general duty: this duty is a ſerious Repentance, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in both words put together. <hi>Return. Eſau</hi> went out from the Church, deſpiſed the Priviledges of it, his Poſterity here is called up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to come back again. <hi>Come; i. e.</hi> Come to God, to him from who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you went away in that Apoſtacy: which two are true Repentance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> away from ſin, a going to God.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:107003:44"/>2. They imply a thorough Repentance, both words laid together; Forſake ſin, and cleave unto God, this is a whole work.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They imply a ſpeedy Repentance, <hi>Return, come.</hi> God is at a word with them, if they will, let them make haſte. Hence, to ſum up all in one, obſerve this</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>When God begins to viſit a ſinning people for their ſins, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects a thorough and ſpeedy Repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Doctrine there are three things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. God <hi>now</hi> expects Repentance: he promiſeth himſelf ſuch an effect, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26 9. hence he calls for it, <hi>Jer.</hi> 26. 12, 13.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God expects <hi>a thorough Repentance,</hi> it is no halving of it with God, when once he hath taken the rod into his hand, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4. 1.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God expects <hi>a ſpeedy Repentance,</hi> God is in haſte, and ſo muſt we, <hi>ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. Of the the firſt; From Gods merciful Nature, who had rather ſinners ſhould repent and live, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. 11. he had rather ſpare then deſtroy, but it muſt be ſo as his Honour may not be wronged, which is near and precious to him, and therefore it muſt be by giving glory to him in a way of Repentance. Hence God when he hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, uſeth delayes, and moves ſlowly in bringing his Judgements.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. Of the ſecond; Becauſe partial Repentance is but a mockery: We owe God all, and therefore in every thing wherein we have offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, we ought to repent and return, and ſeek to make it up. He that doth not repent ſeriouſly of every ſin, doth not repent truly of any ſin; he that doth not return unto God, doth not in truth turn away from his ſin: a half repentance therefore is no repentance at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 3. Of the third:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe this is the laſt means, and therefore if this do it not, what hopes are there remaining of ſuch a peoples Reformation. God takes not the Rod in his hand till he be enforced to it, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. 37. he uſeth all other means firſt, Convictions, Reproofs, Warnings, Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and waits to ſee if theſe will not reach his ends, and work re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; when all theſe fail, then he begins to afflict a people: now if this will not effect it, nothing will, ſuch a people are beyond hopes obſtinate in rebellion, whom Judgements will not awaken to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and therefore God hath little encouragement to uſe any long delayes with ſuch a people.</p>
            <p n="2">2: Becauſe God delayes till he be indeed provoked, and therefore
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:107003:44"/> there is need to make haſte. God in this exalts his Patience to wait a long time upon a rebellious people, but if Patience be worn out, we had need have a care now to our ſelves, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27. 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Here we ſee what is our work to day: God hath begun and made an entrance, and hath been bringing of us on to a ſtage of Judgements, I need not mention the particulars wherein his hand hath been out againſt us. Here you ſee what God expects at our hands.</p>
            <p>Firſt, He muſt have <hi>Repentance,</hi> if you come not to this you do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; if you only <hi>confeſs,</hi> it is but half a Faſt, you muſt <hi>forſake</hi> too.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God will be owned to be juſt, in the moſt retired thoughts of your hearts, he cannot bear it to be found fault withall, of be though: to do any wrong; he will have you to acknowledge, that in all he hath done, he is righteous.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hence you muſt ſee your ſins, your many provocations, your Covenant-breakings, and your particular enormities, you cannot elſe juſtifie God aright, for that is onely done by a ſight of ſin in its being, its hainouſneſs and guilt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God puniſheth for ſin, hence therefore you muſt forſake them you muſt part with thoſe ſins which have parted between God and you: Gods holineſs will keep him at a diſtance from you, ſo long as you keep your ſins, and do not willingly part with them: he cannot love you, till you hate your ſins.</p>
            <p>Secondly, He muſt have a <hi>thorough Repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. You muſt repent of all your ſins, that is, all univerſally, and all particularly, as he comes to diſcover them to you, you muſt be ſure hide none under your tongue, ſpare none, but bring them all forth and confeſs them before God; the leaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a diſtance from God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You muſt amend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
